<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>News from the new-Jerusalem sent by letters from severall parts, relating some hints and observations of that citty, all conspiring in a testimony that renders it exceeding glorious.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 225 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37457</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D86</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27850</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10174866</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10174866</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44694</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37457)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44694)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1381:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>News from the new-Jerusalem sent by letters from severall parts, relating some hints and observations of that citty, all conspiring in a testimony that renders it exceeding glorious.</title>
                  <author>S. P. D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 158, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.D. for Giles Calvert,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: Some Christian letters declaring their severall experiences.</note>
                  <note>"To the Christian reader" signed: S.P.D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life.</term>
               <term>Conversion.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44694:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44694:1"/>
            <p>News from the New-JERUSALEM, Sent by Letters from ſeverall Parts, relating ſome Hints, and Obſervations of that Citty, All conſpiring in a Teſtimony that renders it exceeding Glorious.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Revel. 21. 5.</bibl> And hee that ſate upon the throne ſaid, BEHOLD, I MAKE ALL THINGS NEW.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>G. D.</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the ſigne of the Black-ſpread Eagle, at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:44694:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44694:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader, and more eſpecially to the Saints, that wait upon God in the uſe of Formes.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou haſt here preſented to thy view, a coppy of certain <hi>Letters,</hi> written to private friends, not at all intended for thy uſe: But ſince it is their fate to fall into publick hands; and ſince there are ſomethings in them well worth thy notice and obſervation: <hi>A well-wiſher of thine,</hi> for thy good, hath thought fit to uſher them to thy hand, by writing one letter unto thee; the rather to engage thee, by reading that which is thine own, to take a ſurvey of the whole parcell, that therein thou mayeſt behold, <hi>the breaking forth of God, and the ſpirit that now breathes in many Saints, which ſeems to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie
<pb facs="tcp:44694:3"/>
and promiſe, that God is about to doe ſome great and notable thing for his people, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their long expectations, and as an anſwer to their prayers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But although God be breaking forth upon the world in a greater degree of light and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry then former ages have ſeen: yet thou art to know that we are as yet but in the twi-light: we ſee onely the dawnings of an approaching day; we are at the utmoſt but upon the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and confines of this glory; and therefore (<hi>Reader</hi>) in thy examination of doctrines, and inquiſition after truth, two things would be carefully heeded: Firſt, not to receive eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing for truth, that comes abroad under that notion. Nor ſecondly to reject every thing that is new to thee as errour. Leaſt <hi>thou take darkneſſe for light, and light for darknes.</hi> As thou wouldeſt avoid falling into the gulfe of errour on one hand; ſo beware thou daſh not againſt <hi>the rock Chriſt</hi> on the other; for there may be a dangerous miſcarriage on either ſide.</p>
            <p>This is moſt certain, that whenſoever God, <hi>the father of lights,</hi> begets and brings forth any freſh diſcovery of light and truth in the world: the <hi>Devill, the father of lyes will transform himſelf into an Angel of light;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:44694:3"/>
and will preſs upon the moſt conſcientious<note place="margin">* It is as leaſt a very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that <hi>truth is riſing &amp; ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the earrh;</hi> when er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and deluſion walke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of comming downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note> Chriſtians, his falſities and deluſions, under ſuch ſpecious and plauſible colours, that will <hi>deceive (if t'were poſſible) the very elect.</hi> And this he will doe diverſly, by working up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a different ſubject.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in regard there is but a mixture of light and darknes, in the moſt knowing Saints; he will take advantage by the remainder of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in them, to make them inſtruments to promote errour as well as truth: and the ſeed of errour falling into the ſoyle of this dark principle may grow there for ſome time, till the principle of light wholly overcome and expell this darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, he doth more uſually make uſe of forward, formall profeſſours, and theſe he dare truſt, though they hold forth the truth for a time, becauſe he knows when they fall off, and diſcover themſelves, they will raiſe the greateſt ſcandall, and bring the greateſt odium upon the truth; ſo that its no ſafe rule, to judge of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons by their doctrines, nor of doctrines by the perſons, that brings them.</p>
            <p>Therefore (<hi>Reader</hi>) thou feeſt, what need thou haſt to harken to the Apoſtles counſell; <hi>Try the ſpirits whether they be of God:</hi> leaſt thou feed upon <hi>Scorpions,</hi> and caſt away the <hi>true bread;</hi> leaſt thou abide in darkneſſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:44694:4"/>
ſee not the brightneſſe and glory of that day, that is neer approaching.</p>
            <p>Thou canſt not be ignorant, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as well the old teſtament as the new, beare witneſſe of a glorious day that ſhall ſhine forth in the laſt times, when the <hi>light of the Moon, ſhall be as the light of the Sun, and the light of the Sunne as the light of ſeven dayes,</hi> which as it ſhall be a glorious day, ſo it ſhall be the joyfulleſt day that ever the <hi>Saints</hi> beheld, for it ſhall bee their wedding day; Then ſhall that voyce of acclamation be heard, <hi>Let us be glad and rejoyce and give honour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, for the marriage of the Lambe come, and his wife hath made her ſelfe ready.</hi> To make the <hi>Lambs wife</hi> ready, hath beene the great work of God in the world. How neare we are come to this time, I ſhall not undertake to determine, but much may be gueſſed, by <hi>Gods</hi> preparations for the ſame, for almoſt ſix thouſand yeares, and by his various appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and graduall approaches unto his people from the beginning, to this preſent time, of which take this briefe experimentall <hi>Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though <hi>the Lord our God be one Lord;</hi> and hath ſaid of himſelfe, <hi>I am alone, and there is none beſides me:</hi> yet in another ſenſe hee
<pb facs="tcp:44694:4"/>
hath ſaid, <hi>That two are better then one,</hi> and; <hi>It is not good the man ſhould bee alone;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this <hi>One Onely-wiſe Being,</hi> for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth of his owne glory hath greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted to multiply and bring forth himſelfe in a world of variety and diſtinction, that hee might againe gather up all things into himſelfe, in the moſt perfect and abſolute union: Or in a larger naration take it thus; This one God hath branched and ſpread forth himſelfe, in this great Fabrick of <hi>heaven</hi> and <hi>earth,</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and garniſhed the ſame with infinite variety of his works, and creatures, and then made <hi>man,</hi> the topp of this <hi>creation:</hi> And for the ſpeciall favour he bare unto man, whom he had made after his own likeneſſe, he beſtowed upon him the dominion and Lordſhip of this lower world, or of the whole earth, and in the midſt or chiefeſt place there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, planted a <hi>paradice,</hi> or <hi>garden of pleaſure,</hi> and placed the <hi>man</hi> therein; where hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with his <hi>maker,</hi> in the higheſt enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>creatures:</hi> But <hi>God</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving open a poſterne doore, <hi>(the man being deceived by the Serpent) ſinne entred into the world,</hi> and drew after it at the heeles, all ſorts of <hi>miſery, confuſion, death</hi> and <hi>bondage,</hi> and brought upon the whole <hi>creation</hi> ten thouſand
<pb facs="tcp:44694:5"/>
diſtempers, and diſtractions, fractions, and diviſions, and eſpecially upon <hi>man</hi> the cauſe hereof, who now became nothing elſe but a perfect <hi>map of miſery;</hi> but <hi>God,</hi> to <hi>heale and cure</hi> all this, immediately threw open the <hi>broad gate of glory,</hi> and ſent forth <hi>his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Sonne,</hi> that <hi>by his death and ſufferings,</hi> he might <hi>reſtore all things</hi> into a bleſſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, <hi>redeeme the world out of bondage,</hi> reduce all things to a ſweete harmony and agreement, <hi>reconcile all things to himſelfe both in heaven and in earth,</hi> and gather up all things (thus ſcattered abroad) into a perfect agreement, and the neareſt union, with himſelfe; <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 20. And all this by carrying on a <hi>marriage,</hi> betwixt himſelfe and his <hi>creature man;</hi> And ſo the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>heaven</hi> and <hi>earth</hi> (in a conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion to the <hi>creatures</hi> weakneſſe) becomes a <hi>ſuter</hi> to the loweſt and vileſt earth, which he hath tranſacted, by certain ſteps and grada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, upon this account.</p>
            <p>This, now unhappy <hi>creature man,</hi> through the enmity of his mind, ariſing from the guilt of his diſobedience, looking upon <hi>God</hi> as an <hi>enemy,</hi> ſaith unto him, <hi>Depart from me, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not the knowledge of thy wayes;</hi> But <hi>God</hi> being reſolved not to looſe his <hi>creature,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee had ſet his heart upon him, with an
<pb facs="tcp:44694:5"/>
intent to marry him to <hi>himſelfe;</hi> and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that man in his apoſtate condition, was not able <hi>to dwell with devouring fire, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting burnings,</hi> ſaw it needfull to ſet up cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>vailes and partitions</hi> betwixt <hi>himſelfe,</hi> and his <hi>creature,</hi> that hee might treat with him at a diſtance, and break downe thoſe <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions</hi> one after another, and ſo make nearer and nearer approaches towards his <hi>beloved,</hi> as hee ſhould enure her, and traine her up by degrees, to more ſtrength and maturity.</p>
            <p>Now the ſteps and ſtages by which God makes towards his beloved, are thoſe ſeverall tranſactions or diſpenſations, wherein God from the beginning, and from time to time hath appeared unto her; by which, as by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>medium's,</hi> under and below himſelf, he hath adminiſtred to gain the affections of this coy creature; To this purpoſe, in every addreſs he makes towards her, he appears clad in a new ſuit of apparrell, ſuch as he knew would beſt ſuit with every <hi>age and meaſure, of her ſtature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Gods firſt ſetting forth in this expedition, you have upon record in the beginning of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis. The ſeed of the woman, ſhall breake the Serpents head.</hi> Here <hi>God</hi> keepes himſelfe at a
<pb facs="tcp:44694:6"/>
great diſtance, as if he would but barely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound his buſineſſe, or onely publiſh his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention abroad to the world; as if he would as yet be rather heard then ſeene, and heard on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to whiſper and murmure out his mind, in ſoft and inarticulate ſounds, rather then in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and diſtinct voyce and language; yet hereby he gaines a faint, weake, implicite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, for by this were <hi>the Patriarcks ſaved;</hi> This was the firſt <hi>diſpenſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. The next ſtep <hi>God</hi> takes, is a journey to <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> where he appointed a ſolemne meeting to treat with his <hi>beloved;</hi> Here <hi>God</hi> keepes himſelfe ſtill at a great diſtance, and is faine to make uſe of <hi>Moſes,</hi> (a friend to both parties) as a meet <hi>Mediator</hi> betweene them; Here <hi>God</hi> drew up an agreement of his own hand writing, digeſted into ten Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, offered it to the conſideration of his <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved,</hi> and was afterwards conſented to by each party; but poore <hi>man</hi> (or poore <hi>woman</hi> rather) was ſo ſcared and affrighted with <hi>Gods</hi> attendants, <hi>of thunders, and lightnings, and a thick cloud, the voyce of a trumpet exceeding loud, and ſmoake, and fire, and an earthquake;</hi> that the conſent on the <hi>womans</hi> part, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded rather from feare, then from any great love. This was indeed an hard and harſh <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:44694:6"/>
but ſuch as <hi>divine wiſdome</hi> had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and as ſuited with his deſigne.</p>
            <p>3. After this <hi>God</hi> kept his <hi>beloved</hi> company <hi>fourty yeares in the wilderneſſe, in a pillar of cloud, and a pillar of fire:</hi> And the more to <hi>allure her in this wilderneſſe,</hi> he <hi>pitcht a tent,</hi> and within that (for better accommodation) <hi>he built a tarbernacle,</hi> to treat further with his <hi>beloved;</hi> Here God appointed more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne and frequent meetings, that his <hi>beloved</hi> might get ſome further knowledge of him; In this <hi>tabernacle God</hi> ſhewed his <hi>beloved</hi> an imperfect, dim, <hi>ſhadow</hi> of his <hi>own image or pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,</hi> that ſo ſhe might be able to make ſome gueſſe of his perſon and comely proportion; but a clearer view of himſelfe as yet he gave her not, in regard of her tender ſight which could not behold <hi>majeſty;</hi> therefore <hi>God</hi> held forth himſelfe unto her in certaine darke, ſhaddowie repreſentatations, as <hi>ſacrifices, ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>4. The next journey <hi>God</hi> undertakes, was to <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> where hee gave his <hi>beloved</hi> a prooffe and experiment of his fidelity, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving her a reſt and ſettled habitation, in <hi>a land fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wing with milk and hony,</hi> after her long &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious travail, according to an ancient promiſe, made to her <hi>anceſtours;</hi> and that hee might
<pb facs="tcp:44694:7"/>
acquaint her yet more with himſelfe, and put the greater ſtate upon his negotiation, he built here for his <hi>beloved a magnificent and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pallace:</hi> In this <hi>pallace, God</hi> preſented un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his <hi>beloved</hi> a perfect <hi>ſhadow</hi> of his <hi>owne i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi> that ſhe might be able to make ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter judgment of his perſon, feature &amp; ſtature; Here <hi>God</hi> alſo appeared to his <hi>beloved</hi> in the ſame kinde of repreſentatons as before, but theſe more irradiated, and illuminated by a neerer approach of his glorious and divine preſence.</p>
            <p>And while <hi>God</hi> kept his reſidence in this pallace, the more to draw on the affections of his beloved, he would ſometimes <hi>knock at her</hi> chamber <hi>doore,</hi> and other whiles <hi>looke through the lettice</hi> upon her; but his naked preſence, was an object yet too ſtrong for her ſight.</p>
            <p>5. After this, <hi>God,</hi> to move the more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in his ſuite, and a little to ſtirre the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and move the bowels of his <hi>beloved,</hi> Hee gets on himſelfe a ſute of her owne apparell, <hi>cloathes himſelfe with her owne fleſh,</hi> takes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelfe <hi>her own nature;</hi> and (comming thus neare her) <hi>caught her by guile;</hi> Now the <hi>partition wall</hi> that ſtood betwixt them, is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken downe, the thick <hi>vaile</hi> of <hi>ceremonies</hi> is rent aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder; the old <hi>repreſentatives</hi> are laid
<pb facs="tcp:44694:7"/>
aſide as of no longer uſe. Now was unfolded part of the great miſtery of godlineſſe, <hi>God manifeſt in the fleſh, of Emmanuell or God with us.</hi> Here <hi>God</hi> preſents unto his <hi>beloved</hi> the lively <hi>picture, the expreſſe image and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of his own perſon;</hi> as great <hi>Princes</hi> when they fetch them wives from remote and forraigne parts, are wont to woe by their <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents</hi> and <hi>Ambaſſadours,</hi> and to repreſent themſelves to their <hi>Ladies,</hi> by their own <hi>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures;</hi> Hereupon his <hi>beloved</hi> gives her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and now both parties are agreed.</p>
            <p>But between all theſe woing paſſages and expreſſions of love on <hi>Gods</hi> part; O how many hard hearted denyals? How many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civill repulſes? How many unmannerly revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and ſtartings back? How much uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty and inconſtancy, falſeneſſe and perſidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, doth <hi>God</hi> meet withall on the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans part? Never did the wild <hi>Aſſes Colt,</hi> that is brought forth and bred in the <hi>wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> diſcover ſo much peeviſhneſſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſſe; Inſomuch that <hi>God</hi> (who was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to gaine her by faire meanes or by fowle) was ſaine to chaſtiſe her with 430, <hi>yeares bondage in Aegypt;</hi> to nurture her (by <hi>leading her about) forty yeares, in a vaſt, howling wilderneſſe;</hi> and (for <hi>her fornications
<pb facs="tcp:44694:8"/>
and whoredomes</hi> after all this) to <hi>impriſon, manacle,</hi> and <hi>fetter</hi> her, by <hi>ſeaventy yeares captivity in Babylon;</hi> But notwithſtanding all this, <hi>Gods</hi> affection being ſtill the ſame, he held faſt his purpoſe and reſolution, to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his ſute to the utmoſt, and to make this untoward woman, a meet helpe for himſelfe, though it ſhould coſt him the life and blood of his <hi>Sonne</hi> and <hi>heire,</hi> which now he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in part performed.</p>
            <p>6. Therefore <hi>God,</hi> (who wel knew the muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and inconſtancy of fleſh and blood) that hee might at laſt come within his <hi>beloved,</hi> and at one blow ſtrike the match dead, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther put ſo much life into it as might ſecure it from all hazard of revocation and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; He ſecretly winds and inſinuates him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into her heart; conveies his owne ſpirit into her inward parts; <hi>makes her partaker of his own divine nature;</hi> ſo that now they are not onely <hi>one fleſh,</hi> but <hi>one ſpirit;</hi> Now there is but one heart and ſoul betwixt them; <hi>God</hi> hath ſo gotten into her heart, that he can boldly talke to her, as to his wife, and ſnee to him, as to her husband. Now ſhe can ſay, <hi>My well beloved is mine, and I am his;</hi> nothing is wanting to compleat this marriage but the <hi>ſpouſes making her ſelfe ready.</hi> Thus you ſee
<pb facs="tcp:44694:8"/>
               <hi>Gods</hi> graduall proceeding in this undertaking, and how neare the buſineſſe is brought to a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall concluſion.</p>
            <p>And becauſe there remaines now but a <hi>vaile</hi> or two more, that keeps up a diſtance betwixt <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Spouſe,</hi> which being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, the union would bee entire and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute; therefore he reſolves forth with to break through theſe alſo; and inaſmuch as <hi>God</hi> (or <hi>God-Man</hi>) hath already uncloathed himſelfe of naturall fleſh (of which the <hi>rending of the vaile of the Temple was a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure</hi>) by <hi>ſuffering it to be crucified</hi> that hee might enter into ſpirit, or return into the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt glory of the <hi>Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>7. So the <hi>Saints</hi> or miſticall body, in confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity unto <hi>Chriſt</hi> the head, doe uncloath them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the rags of corrupt and ſinfull fleſh, by ſuffering it to be crucified, that <hi>the divine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or image of God</hi> may ſhine forth in the humane, till <hi>God</hi> diſcover his dwelling in the fleſh of the <hi>Saints,</hi> as he dwelt in the fleſh of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and afterwards this fleſh be taken up into ſpirit.</p>
            <p>8. In order whereunto <hi>God</hi> hath ſo farre ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced that he is pulling downe the partitions that remaine. Hee is tearing the vaile, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the naturall, but of the miſticall fleſh of
<pb facs="tcp:44694:9"/>
               <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or that whole adminiſtration of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> conſiſting in formes and ordinances.</p>
            <p>9 Yea, <hi>God</hi> is not onely taking downe this <hi>tabernacle</hi> of the miſticall fleſh of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but he is deſtroying, the miſticall or ſpirituall fleſh of the <hi>Saints</hi> (if I may ſo call it) ſtanding in their own righteouſneſſe; that good perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion they have had of themſelves, rais'd up and built upon their qualifications, religious du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and performances. The <hi>reading of this vaile,</hi> will rend the heart, and <hi>the caule of the liver</hi> of many <hi>Saints,</hi> becauſe moſt of their comfort hath ſprung from this roote; moſt of their evidence hath beene layd upon this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: This muſt needes ſtartle them to have <hi>their heaven, their evidence for heaven</hi> thus ſhaken; and this (by comparing together <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 26, 27. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3 13.) I conceive will bee the ultimate and finall accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that place in <hi>Haggai, 2. chap. 6. I will ſhake the heauens and the earth, and the ſea, and the dry land, and I will ſhake all nations, and the deſire of all nations ſhall come.</hi> This great work hath <hi>God</hi> begunne to take in hand; <hi>To ſhake the old heaven and earth, and to make new;</hi> To deſtroy our own righteouſneſſe, and inſtead thereof to bring forth <hi>Chriſt</hi> in ſpirit, who is <hi>the Lord our righteouſneſſe;</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:44694:9"/>
how does the <hi>devill</hi> rage and ſtrive by his ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems on all hands to make this child an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bortive? Without doubt <hi>God</hi> is removing out of fleſhly adminiſtrations, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon his people to come up and ſerve him in that which is more ſpirituall; <hi>God</hi> is withdrawing from formes, that hee may draw his people after him into ſpirit and power.</p>
            <p>Nor is this intended to take thoſe off from formes, that enjoy <hi>Gods</hi> preſence in them; but to give an account of thoſe that walke not informes, and to call thoſe higher then formes, from whom <hi>God</hi> is apparently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted in formes; for there are divers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and meaſures of <hi>chriſtians;</hi> Some finde <hi>God</hi> (it may be) in every ordinance; others finde him in none at all; ſome enjoy his preſence in one publique ordinance and not in another; others <hi>God</hi> meets in their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate duties, but not in the publique; Let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>Saint</hi> abide in the ſtation where <hi>God</hi> ſets him, till hee ſay unto him, <hi>come up hither:</hi> And why ſhouldſt thou wonder at this? Hath it not been the ſad complaint of many ſerious <hi>chriſtians,</hi> for theſe many yeares, that ordinances have been barren to them, and themſelves barren in the uſe of them? What
<pb facs="tcp:44694:10"/>
ſhould the meaning of this bee, but that <hi>God</hi> cals upon ſuch to looke out for higher diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of himſelfe, then attend thoſe old wayes?</p>
            <p>This thing many poore ſoules have beene ignorant off, and therefore have layne downe under the burden of greif and ſorrow, as if <hi>God</hi> had utterly forſaken them.</p>
            <p>It is not denyed, but that as there may bee the forme of godlineſſe without the power; ſo the forme and power may both ſtand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; but there is a time when <hi>God</hi> will goe forth, out of <hi>forme</hi> into <hi>power,</hi> out of <hi>fleſh</hi> into <hi>ſpirit;</hi> out of <hi>formall</hi> and <hi>fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adminiſtrations</hi> into that which is more <hi>ſpirituall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>formes</hi> (or this miſticall fleſh of <hi>Chriſt</hi>) have beene as <hi>Jonahs gourd,</hi> under which the <hi>Saints</hi> have long repoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, enjoyed much ſweet ſhelter and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and therefore cannot beare the parting with them, neither in themſelves nor others; but now if <hi>God</hi> upon deſigne, to carry up his people to more ſpirituallity, hath prepared a <hi>worme</hi> at the <hi>root</hi> of this <hi>gourd</hi> purpoſely to kill and dry it up, <hi>doſt thou well to be angry</hi> Jonah? <hi>Yes</hi> (thou wilt ſay) <hi>I doe well to bee angry to the death,</hi> for ſome have not onely left
<pb facs="tcp:44694:10"/>
off ordinances, but preach them downe and ſpeake contemptibly of them. <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Blame not all that have left them off, for ſome may have done it upon a right ground; As for thoſe that ſpeake contemptible of them <hi>I</hi> excuſe them uot at all; but this I ſay, If there be a <hi>worme</hi> at their <hi>root</hi> and they muſt needes dye, then (as <hi>Calvin</hi> once ſaid of the <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> of old, ſo ſay I of thoſe) <hi>Let them have an honourable buriall;</hi> As the weake <hi>Saints</hi> yet under formes would not be deſpiſed by thoſe above them, ſo let them not be harſh accuſers of thoſe that ſee their liberty and ſtand faſt in it; This was the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> rule to preſerve peace and love, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. betweene diſſenting brethren; For further ſatisfaction in this Poynt, I referre theee to the 28. Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> was <hi>three dayes in the grave,</hi> and then roſe out of it againe; <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath beene in formes; to ſome he is ſtill, to others he is riſen out of formes; Tell me, wouldſt thou have theſe ſeeke <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Sepulchre, in formes, when they ſee he is riſen, and perhaps have been told by an <hi>Angel, he is not here, he is riſen?</hi> Be not weaker then the weak <hi>diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> who hearing their <hi>Lord</hi> was riſen, depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the <hi>ſepulchre;</hi> after which it was
<pb facs="tcp:44694:11"/>
not long that they heard hee was riſen, by ſome that had ſeen him; nor long after that againe, that he appeared unto them, and raiſed up their faith which was ſinking and ready to dye. What doſt thou meane (poore <hi>Saint</hi>) that with <hi>Mary</hi> lyeſt puling and <hi>weeping at the ſepulchre,</hi> when as thy <hi>Savionr is riſen?</hi> Why doſt thou <hi>ſeeke the living among the dead?</hi> Thou ſeeſt how many diſpenſations <hi>God</hi> hath paſſed through (beſides other inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening, leſſe remarkable appearances, which, have been omitted;) God was in the fleſh of <hi>Ghriſt;</hi> but that having done its office, he lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it aſide; God is entred upon a diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſpirit, and cals upon his <hi>pſouſe</hi> to follow him; but ſhe is ſo fallen in love with this ſute of old cloathes, this garment of fleſh, that ſhe is loath to lay it aſide, as if ſhe meant to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But tell me, wouldſt thou tye God alwayes to one diſpenſation? or if thou cauſt not, but that hee will advance higher till hee come to the higheſt, wilt thou tarry behinde him, and dwell alwayes in the ſame place? Doſt thou not know that the conſummation of Gods marriage with thee, is the compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thine owne happineſſe? And doſt thou not ſee that God is gone before thee? Doſt thou not hear him calling thee, <hi>come up hither?</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:44694:11"/>
If God be gone before, why doſt linger and laggar behinde? Doſt thou ſtand ſtill and pleaſe thy ſelfe with beholding thy preſent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments? or doſt thou look back and admire thy former good worke? Remember what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith was his practiſe; <hi>forgetting thoſe things that are behinde, and reacoing forth to thoſe things that are before, I preſs towards the mark &amp;c.</hi> Call to mind alſo <hi>Peters</hi> admonition, <hi>Looking for, and haſtening unto the comming of the day of God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>God forbid, that thou ſhouldeſt <hi>limit the holy one of Iſrael;</hi> that thou ſhouldeſt tye and binde down God to any form or adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, longer then will ſerve his own deſigne: And God forbid, that thou ſhouldeſt ſtop and ſtay in a diſpenſation, after thou findeſt he is departed from it.</p>
            <p>God took up diſpenſations onely to ſerve a turn; to bring about his deſigne of making his creature happy, by its union with himſelf; The finiſhing &amp; laying down of diſpenſations, is the perfecting and finiſhing of the creatures happineſſe, and the introducing of that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous day before hinted; which will be by the ariſing of the <hi>Sunne of Righteouſneſſe,</hi> not in one Horizon of the world onely, but through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>whol earth and heaven;</hi> which <hi>day of the
<pb facs="tcp:44694:12"/>
Lord,</hi> as it ſhould be to us the moſt deſirable thing in the worle, ſo it ſhould ſeem to be at hand, and to ſtand knocking at our doores; by ſome glimpſes of glory that appear already, and particularly by thoſe rayes and beams of light, that ſtream forth in theſe enſuing letters.</p>
            <p>In ſome of theſe Letters, thou ſhalt hear the ſtammerings and liſpings of children, rather then <hi>a pure language</hi> or perfect ſpeaking; but let not that offend thee: If thou art a Father of children, a thouſand to one, thou art not ſo moroſe and auſtere, but thou haſt taken delight to hear thy children prattle, though they ſpake but half words, and broken ſentences; and why ſhould it trouble thee to hear thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, the children of thine, and their heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father expreſſe themſelves in ſuch language as they are able: Is is not ſaid, <hi>Out of the mouth of Babes and ſucklings, thou haſt ordained ſtrength; or, thou haſt perfected praiſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In others of theſe Letters, perhaps thou mayſt meet with ſome things that may be <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxes and hard ſayings to thee, which thou canſt not beare;</hi> but ſit not in judgement to condemn this neither, as if thou wouldeſt take upon thee to know all things: ſuſpend, cenſure, till thou haſt a clearer light (of which ſurely thou art not out of hope): perhaps that day may
<pb facs="tcp:44694:12"/>
not be far from thee, wherein thou ſhalt ſpeak and underſtand <hi>harder ſayings, and higher my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries,</hi> then thou ſhalt meet withall in theſe Letters.</p>
            <p>Nor yet doe I undertake to juſtifie all that is written in them; <hi>'Tis yet but the dawning of the day; The clear eſt principle</hi> (for ought I know) <hi>hath a mixture of earth and darkneſſe in it; The light is yet neyther cleare nor dark; 'tis neyther night nor day, but in the evening time it ſhall be light, Zach</hi> 14. 6, 7. And then 'tis poſſible an higher appearance in the ſame perſons that wrote theſe Letters, may <hi>judge ſome things in them to the fire, as hey and ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, thou ſhalt find one letter among the reſt, written by a precious <hi>Soule, walking in darkneſſe and having no light;</hi> wrapt up and mantled in a black night of trouble and dejection of Spirit: Let this Letter (that may ſeem not to ſuit with his fellowes) ſerve as ſharpe ſawce, with ſweet meat, to give a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reliſh to the reſt: Doubtleſſe, <hi>the Lord hath a gracious deſigne upon this good ſoule, and hath but withdrawn himſelf for a little moment, that witheverlaſting mercies he may imbrace it;</hi> that he may diſcover himſelf unto this ſoule, to be nothing but light and love,
<pb facs="tcp:44694:13"/>
               <hi>and bring forth himſelf in this ſmoaking flack, in an higher and brighter flame of light and glory, in a more glorious appearance then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: And when God ſhall bring this to paſſe, if thou pleaſe, in the mean time, to taſte of his teares, peradventure when he reaps his har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, thou mayeſt be made partaker of his joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Septemb. 24. 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>A wel-wiſher of thine, and of the truth, as it is in <hi>Jeſus.</hi> S. P. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44694:13"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 20. line 16. dele <hi>of.</hi> pag. 21. lin. 16. for <hi>new,</hi> read <hi>more.</hi> pag. 23. lin. 14. read <hi>with ſpiritvall.</hi> p. 38. l. 10. r. <hi>conſider.</hi> l. 13. r. <hi>the creature.</hi> l. 16. r. <hi>as with a creator.</hi> l 17. r. <hi>as with a Father.</hi> p. 40. l. 3. r. <hi>billowing.</hi> l. 22. f. <hi>doth,</hi> r. <hi>were.</hi> p. 41. l. 1. r. <hi>a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then whom.</hi> p. 41. l. 17. f <hi>meaneſt,</hi> r. <hi>neareſt.</hi> l. 24. r. <hi>was higher.</hi> p. 42. l. 12. r. <hi>ſon.</hi> p. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. l. 3. f. <hi>lo,</hi> r. <hi>to.</hi> p. 54. l. 5. r. <hi>the beſt.</hi> p. 56. l. 19. and p. 57. l. 2. r. <hi>ſpirits.</hi> p. 58. l. 26. r. <hi>ſwords.</hi> p. 60. l. 10. r. <hi>overrunne.</hi> p. 61. l. 22. r. <hi>not mov'd.</hi> l. 24. r. <hi>ſcattering.</hi> p. 62. l. 7. r. <hi>accomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> l. 22. r. <hi>having.</hi> p. 63. l. 9. r. <hi>And this a.</hi> l. 18. r. <hi>who ripe for.</hi> p. 66. l. 3. f. <hi>our,</hi> r. <hi>one.</hi> l. 14. r. <hi>is known.</hi> p. 67. l. 3. r. <hi>raiſers of.</hi> l. 5. r. <hi>neare.</hi> p. 91. l. 9. r. <hi>onenes.</hi> p. 105. l. 18. r. <hi>not imagined.</hi> p. 145. l. 28. r. <hi>externall.</hi> p. 146. l. 19. f. <hi>ſure,</hi> r. <hi>free.</hi> p. 149. l. 18. r. <hi>the box is in your heart.</hi> p. 145. l. 6. r. <hi>this taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle.</hi> p. 155. l. 24. f. <hi>torne,</hi> r <hi>to me.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb facs="tcp:44694:14"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:44694:14"/>
            <head>News from the New-<hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> ſent by Letters from ſeverall Parts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>1. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Deare Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have received your loving Letter, and therewith Mrs. <hi>M.</hi> kind token, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my opening, I had thought had beene ſome Book: Her remembrance of me doth much refreſh me, and ſhe is made therein an inſtrument of making me partaker of much of the love and goodneſſe of God. I had beene in ſome ſad (but yet withall ſweet) thoughts but juſt before they came o me; when they came, I ſaid, <hi>theſe are to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44694:15"/>
wipe away teares from mine eyes, and that love that ſent them aſſuredly will.</hi> Sir I pray you remember me to her, and thanke her, and if I may come with good company to her, I ſhall be glad to give her a viſit when I come to <hi>London,</hi> that is, with the <hi>Father,</hi> and with his <hi>Son Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> for there is our fellowſhip, without whom 'tis a dry feaſt and a fruitleſſe viſit; nevertheleſſe I ſhall (I truſt) be willing to be ſeen of her barren, or as I am, bee it howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; for wee neither ſtand nor fall to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent abillities or actings.</p>
               <p>Sir, For your deſire of ſomething to bee written touching the firſt and ſecond <hi>appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Chriſt,</hi> I wiſh I were but freſh to give you my thoughts I had thereof this morning; but after twice preaching this day, and now after ſupper I am more diſpoſed to ſleep then write: Your inquiry is after two things, the difference between them, and the traſition or paſſing over of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> from the one to the other; For the firſt, It ſhall only acquaint you with ſome places of <hi>ſcripture</hi> which to me doe ſeeme to hold forth the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two, and they are 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5, 11, 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 28. by which <hi>ſcriptures</hi> it may appeare, that the firſt appearance of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is, <hi>unto Faith;</hi> The ſecond is, <hi>unto Salvation;</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:44694:15"/>
In the firſt he is <hi>made our ſinne;</hi> his ſecond is <hi>without ſin;</hi> our <hi>fellowſhip</hi> with him in the firſt is called, <hi>Planting in the likeneſſe of his death;</hi> our <hi>fellowſhip</hi> with him in the latter is called, <hi>Planting in the likeneſſe of his reſurrection.</hi> The firſt is called <hi>ſufferings, the ſufferings of Chriſt, ver.</hi> 11. of that place in <hi>Peter;</hi> as if it conteined and were made up of nothing elſe; The other is called, <hi>the glory that ſhould follow.</hi> And in that <hi>chapter</hi> it may appeare (at leaſt it doth ſo to me at preſent) that the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> then were cheifly acquainted with the promiſe and expectation of it to come, when <hi>Peter</hi> wrote this; and indeed the glory of the firſt appearance of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was yet very bright, for it was to have its time and ſeaſon; as it hath, through all ages ſince and in this preſent age even with thoſe on whom his ſecond appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is dawned: But if you ſay. All theſe are but externall carracters and diſtinctions of thoſe two appearrnces, but what is the formall and intrinſecall difference between them? I ſhall give you my apprehenſion thereof in brief thus.</p>
               <p>The firſt appearance of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance in <hi>fleſh,</hi> without us, <hi>bearing our ſinne,</hi> and <hi>fulfilling all legall righteouſneſſe,</hi> and thereby becomming the object and meanes of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44694:16"/>
faith to us, whereby to <hi>draw neere to God</hi> unto <hi>reconciliation;</hi> And faith acting upon this diſcovery of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his love through that miniſtration, was (I conceive) that that brought in the ſupplies of all our hope and comfort from time to time, and nouriſhed all grace and holineſſe in our hearts, till the <hi>ariſing of this day Starre in us,</hi> becomming our <hi>ſpirituall righteouſneſſe,</hi> and ſufficiencie for all things, <hi>the end of our faith,</hi> and <hi>our ſalvation it ſelfe</hi> in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
               <p>That which makes this the leſſe knowne, and the more hard to be knowne, is becauſe there are degrees in it, and that which is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of one degree of it (ſuppoſe a higher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree) is not found in a lower degree, and ſo we know it not when it is in us and among us, becauſe we find it not in ſuch an eminent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; As for example, <hi>we ſee not yet all ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies put under us;</hi> and that <hi>glorious redemption of the body,</hi> we yet underſtand not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for all theſe things are but parts and appendices to the ſecond <hi>appearance of Chriſt;</hi> but all theſe waite onely for the acknowledgement of this day, this ſecond appearance, <hi>Chriſt in us, the day Starre riſen in our hearts;</hi> for as the <hi>power and priviledge of becomming ſonnes,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:44694:16"/>
followed upon the receiving and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of his firſt <hi>appearance;</hi> ſo ſhall all the priviledges annexed to his ſecond <hi>appearance,</hi> bee made good to us upon the acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, when it ſhall bee proclaimed within us, and when it ſhall diſcover it ſelfe upon us; and as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſayes to the <hi>woman</hi> of <hi>Samaria, If thou kneweſt the gift of God, and who it is that ſaith unto thee, give me water to drink, thou wouldeſt have asked of him, and he would have given thee living water:</hi> So when wee ſhall bee acquainted what a mighty <hi>one</hi> dwels in us, we ſhall finde our ſelves to be <hi>at the end of our faith,</hi> and <hi>in the poſſeſſion of all ſalvation:</hi> For <hi>He is the reſurrection and the life;</hi> Hee is <hi>redemption;</hi> and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>God</hi> lyes not in, nor is brought on, by any outward circumſtances; The kingdom of God is within you; It comes not with obſervation; ſo that from the premiſes I am bold to pronounce, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> being revealed in ſpirit, in many, The ſecond <hi>appearance</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is dawned upon the world, and 'tis amongſt us though we know it not, or ſcarcely know it; The <hi>redemption of the body</hi> is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and all things beginne to bee new, and to have a new face and appearance to us, ſo far forth as we are changed and ſpiritualli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44694:17"/>
Nor need this be ſtrange, That the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>appearance</hi> ſhould lurke and bee a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in the world, a while, any more then his firſt <hi>appearance,</hi> which was concealed for thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares and ſcarce taken notice off, ſave by <hi>Herod,</hi> when he murdered the <hi>Infants;</hi> Only you may ſay, that this is more in glory! but conſider, the <hi>glory</hi> is inward, and ſo is the <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance,</hi> and therefore the leſſe ſubject to the notice of others, and yet it is proclaimed through the world, under the voyce of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, Blaſphemy, Antichriſt,</hi> the great <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. Doth not the <hi>ſpirit</hi> ſay. <hi>The day of the Lord ſhall ſo come as a Theifi in the night?</hi> and is it not ſo come on moſt <hi>Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors?</hi> inſomuch that they on whom it is come, ſcarce know it, or receive it; And ſhall that which is propheſied of, as a ſigne of it, become a ſiumbling block in its way? <hi>Behol a I come as a Theife,</hi> ſayes <hi>Chriſt; Chriſt</hi> is come as a <hi>theife,</hi> and we ſay 'tis not He; He would be known of his comming if it were, <hi>Yee fooles and blind, yee know not the Scriptures, &amp;c.</hi> This comming of his, the primitive times had it (and eſpecially ſome among them as <hi>Paul</hi> who was called extraordinarily by <hi>Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in him;</hi> and <hi>John that was raviſht in ſpirit, and ſaw the Lords day</hi>) as <hi>Abraham,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44694:17"/>
Iſaack</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> had the promiſed land they were ſojourners in; but there, was a long bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage in <hi>Aegypt</hi> to be undergone by their <hi>ſeed</hi> ere they came to it, whereunto anſwers our long captivity under <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> but the time draws near, wee ſhall ſhortly heare that voyce, <hi>Ariſe, ſhine, for thy light is come, the glory of the Lord is riſen upon thee;</hi> and this ſecond <hi>appearance,</hi> this <hi>day ſtarre</hi> will make the <hi>ſtars</hi> of the <hi>night</hi> to diſappeare, or the <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of the firſt <hi>appearance</hi> to goe down, which is all that I ſhall ſay now to the ſecond part of your inquiry; As this increaſes, the other will decreaſe; no other period of it doe I know; for we are all brought forth firſt <hi>under the law,</hi> and ſo come to <hi>know Chriſt after the fleſh,</hi> and reape the fruit and comfort of his firſt <hi>appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> ere we know him in us as <hi>ſalvation</hi> and <hi>glory;</hi> but whether the <hi>Lord</hi> will alwayes obſerve this <hi>method,</hi> I cannot ſay, rather I think he will not, for 'tis ſaid, <hi>we ſhall not all dye, but ſhall be changed;</hi> wee ſhall not all paſſe under forms, be trained up under the <hi>law,</hi> but ſhall immediately be changed. <hi>Chriſts appearance</hi> to us is the rule of all walking and converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; His appearance being known to us onely in the fleſh, as a <hi>Reconciler, a Miniſter of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion,</hi> is the reaſon of our walking in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44694:18"/>
forms; when hee appeares to us nakedly in ſpirit, as being all to us and in us himſelfe immediately, and alone, then he delivers us into a glorious liberty above all outward forms.</p>
               <p>In that place in <hi>Peter</hi> that ſpeakes of the <hi>fuflerings of Chriſt,</hi> and that <hi>glory that ſhould follow,</hi> I may ſeeme ſtrange to you to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that <hi>following glory</hi> of the body as I doe, but beare with me therein, I doe ſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it of the glorious appearances of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his in ſpirit; nor can I give you my reaſons for it now.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What you write of the difficulty of getting out of the fleſh of Chriſt, and the letter of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture:</hi> I wonder not at, ſeeing we never have <hi>gotten</hi> in, without a divine power and life; and therefore to get through unto the holieſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſame Almighty power, is impoſſible.</p>
               <p>It is no little advance after we are brought in, to look out further and higher; till which time, the witneſſes lie dead in us in the ſtreets, and then that voyce hath been heard, <hi>Come up hither;</hi> and we are aſcending or aſcended, whileſt we are making up in the Lord; There is the Lord in us aſcending, who came down, and none elſe can aſcend but hee.</p>
               <p>As for that I wrote concerning the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44694:18"/>
of Chriſt and his comming ſpoken off in Scripture, <hi>that I know no other comming of Chriſt to judgement, but his ſpirituall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, or appearance in ſpirit (for as for the fleſh, that hath done its work) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is he ſaid, to come in the glory of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of his holy Angels; alſo in flaming fire with his mighty Angels, which is ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. That his comming is nothing but his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing; and that all fleſh is a vaile upon him, from under which he is comming, and caſting it off, making his arme bare; That the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes of all raiſed, ſhall be ſpirituall, like unto his; which is alſo held forth in that expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Apoſtle,</hi> 2 Theſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<hi>The Spirit of his mouth, and the brightneſſe of his comming, which amounts to a ſpirituall appearance and manifeſtation. That this comming, and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is graduall, and hath beenon foot from the beginning of the world, and ſtill goes on, and will be compleated in due time. That the judgement Day which we expect, is nothing elſe, but the perfect and univerſall Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his righteouſnes; his generall and full manifeſtation unto all by his riſing up in all, who is the head and root of all, and making all ſpirituall; for the Kingdom of God is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you: there riſeth up this judgement ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44694:19"/>
upon the world, by which you might under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, how I take that place in the</hi> Corinths Till he come; <hi>namely in ſpirit, when as ſaid, I know no other appearance of his to be but in ſpirit: That hee is entred into ſpirit, and therefore we cannot think he will be perfected in the fleſh (for his Kingdome commeth not by obſervation):</hi> So I think, and ſpeak, and write ſtill: <hi>Though I have known Chriſt after the fleſh, yet hence forth know I him no more.</hi> God hath manifeſted his love and power in that man Chriſt, and in that fleſh which he took, and ſhewed what he will doe in all the Elect, by a ſpirit of power and love, <hi>Redeem, Save, Kill, Quicken, Raiſe, Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie;</hi> and this ſpirit and power of God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in the Elect, is the appearing of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt</hi> in them, both in his <hi>weaknes</hi> and in his <hi>power,;</hi> in his <hi>Cradle, Croſſe, Grave, and in heavenly places, at the right hand of the Father in his full glory. This is the Kingdom of God that comes not by obſervation:</hi> This is, <hi>Chriſt is us, the hops of glory;</hi> who ſhall come by degrees &amp; appear to be (the) glory: He is our life hid, and he is dead in us, and we in him, who ſhall appear and bring us forth with him in glory, being our <hi>Head, Root,</hi> the quickning Spirit, and which doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44694:19"/>
a perſonall appearance of Jeſus Chriſt the Son of man, conſiſting of ſoule and body, to and with the Saints, when he is perfectly formed in them; and what can this appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance be but ſpirituall, in the glory of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the holy Angels, according as the <hi>hodyes,</hi> the <hi>vile bodies</hi> of all the Saints ſhall be in the reſurrection, where it riſeth a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall body, though ſown a naturall body; and then an end of fleſh, and blood, and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo farre the Scripture leads us, and wee muſt not be intruders into theſe things, whileſt God openeth not the doore unto us: Wee are the Sonnes of God, but it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be; In that appearance ſhall be ſeen, the ſutableneſſe of the Saints unto him: Loe I and the children whom God hath given me! and then ſhall be eternall union betwixt God and Chriſt, and Chriſt and the Saints, yet with diſtinction and ſubordination: The head, the body, the root, and the branches, the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and the wife: Chriſt in God, and the Saints in Chriſt, and ſo in the Father; one in another, and perfect in one. Thus I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you the brief, yet full coppy of what is written in mee, ſo farre as I can read, in way of anſwer to your queries; and if you ſhall put me to read it over again, and ſhew me any
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44694:20"/>
miſtakes; you ſhall doe mee no diſpleaſure. As God openeth himſelf in us, ſo we diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver theſe things, and I ſhall be ready to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcover what is diſcovered, though I diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my miſtakes with all: for we are very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned in reading what the ſpirit hath written in us, till it come in a large letter, as it will doe, that we may read it running.</p>
               <trailer>This is all I have liberty to ſay at prefent, </trailer>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Salute from me all our friends, with you.</salute>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:44694:20"/>
               <head>2. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My dear friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N whom I have rejoyced; I hold my ſelfe bound to acquaint you with the wonderfull dealings of my God with me: It is ſo, that I am called into judgement, and the Books are opened, and the booke of life is opened, and I am judged according to all things which are written in the books: Yet neither of theſe books is that <hi>Bible-book</hi> which we have hug'd ſo long, as our onely happineſſe; I would not hore now be miſtaken: for I doe not, ſay this; judgement is not ſpoken off in the <hi>Bible,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks out of which I am judged; for that they are, both of them: and yet I ſay, that the <hi>Bible</hi> in the letter of it, as it is bound up there, is not the book: I would not for a world take away any thing from the <hi>Bible,</hi> or any of the excellency of that which is therein written; but I would have it ſet in the right place: I would not have it taken for God himſelfe, and yet God is in it, and the letter
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44694:21"/>
of it is a very ſweet manifeſtation of God, but it is not God; though God (I ſay) be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in this fleſh: But <hi>though wee have knowne things after the fleſh; yet henceforth we will know them ſo no more:</hi> for indeed, except wee come through the fleſh, which is the vail, we cannot enter into the holieſt: for the outward Court is given to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and it ſhall not bee meaſured: wee all deſire and ſtrive to enter into reſt, the <hi>Lord</hi> give us hearts therefore, that we faile not, becauſe of unbeliefe: But indeed our lives and alſo our ſpirits, are ſo full of prejudicate opinions, that wee are apt to think the worſt of every thing; whereas if we were the <hi>children</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and like our <hi>Father;</hi> we then ſhould live in <hi>God,</hi> which is <hi>love:</hi> yea, we ſhould then be made one with this love. Certainly, we may feare, that thoſe <hi>Children</hi> are baſely begotten, that doe not in any way reſemble their <hi>Father.</hi> Deare friend, ſuch a like generation have we begotten amongſt us, for if we were like our <hi>Father,</hi> we then ſhould <hi>hope all things, beleeve all things; think no evill,</hi> not be lifted up in our ſelves, but <hi>thinke of every one better then of our ſelves:</hi> But though the <hi>ſeed</hi> of the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> be ſowen amongſt us, yet I ſay againe, I would not bee miſtaken by you, for I am not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44694:21"/>
againſt the uſe of the Bible, for I ſee a true ſweet, lovely ſpirit in the writings of it: though yet I would have you know, that I dare not juſtifie all things as they lye in the letter of it; not becauſe the truth is not in it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the abuſe of that truth by the falſ tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of it: for every one when he tranſlates a Coppy, writes it as he thinks fit, and ſo puts in and leaves out according to his concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and we all are not ignorant what hands theſe coppies have come thorow; I beſeech you therefore to wait upon that one ſpirit which is in you, he it is that ſhall lead you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all truth, and I am ſure that when God hath written his own truth within you; then you will be able (as well as the Apoſtles) to write a Bible or any book elſe without you; I am very confident, did the Apoſtles live in our dayes, they would be exceedingly grieved to ſee us appropriate the ſpirit onely to them, when indeed the ſpirit cannot be confined, for it is God himſelf; and this God is in you, and with you, though you know it not ſo well as I could wiſh you did; Let us therefore leave off all our appropriations and diſtinctions, and then doe you tell me, what you finde but God; we have been apt indeed to ſay, <hi>Lo, hear he is, and there he is;</hi> but this is a lye, for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44694:22"/>
he is every where, and he is not any where, as confin'd or diſtinct from himſelf: I beſeech you therefore in the bowels of mercy, that you be carefull what you doe.</p>
               <p>I have one thing to acquaint you with, which indeed was the cauſe of my preſent writing, and its this: That ſeeing (as I have told you) the great day of the Lord is come upon me; and every thing is brought into judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I cannot but minde you of one thing which paſt betwixt us, and it was this; you told me once of your viſiting a maid, which ſaid, that ſhe lived in heaven, and above the Bible, even in God, and by the Revelations of his own ſpirit, which much ſtumbled both you and me: Now I am come to tell you that this maid is riſen in me, and that I know now what ſhe meant, being by the wonderful goodnes of my God, taken in to the ſame life my ſelf, and it is but lately accompliſhed upon my ſoule: Shee meant therefore above the letter of that word in the Bible; that indeed, <hi>was dead too her, but ſhe lived, in the ſpirit and life of it, which was, and is, in God himſelf:</hi> and this is the life which we all have groaned after; and yet (when God comes to take us out of thoſe graves of ſin, and ſelf apropriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and to looſe thoſe Chains and Bonds
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44694:22"/>
which we have (in our darkneſſe and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) been brought into by diſtinctions) we are afraid of him; and not onely, like <hi>Mary, take him for the Gardner;</hi> but wee are even afraid, that it is Satan himſelf: trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed (as we call it) into an Angel of light, when indeed, that is the very Satan that tels us ſo: though he ſets before us a ſeeming good; but we are not ignorant of his <hi>wiles:</hi> This was the <hi>Apple</hi> which he deceived our Mother <hi>Eve</hi> withall, <hi>even this ſeeming good, and hath ever ſince cauſed us to ſurfeit with it:</hi> even to take things that are not, for what they are in truth: therefore take notice by the way, that thoſe things are not, that ſeem to be; or viſibly doe appear to our ſight, but the things that are inviſible, and cannot appear to our fleſhly ſight, thoſe are the things in truth: and therefore take notice of this, that all this outward frame of things which doth appeare to our fleſhly ſight, is but a reſemblance, or a figure of him which is inviſible, and cannot be ſeen but with a pure ſpirituall ſight; I ſpeak all this, for your and others ſakes; which yet ſtick in the fleſh of Chriſt: <hi>For I bleſſe my God,</hi> I am got through it, even within the vaile; and I ſee him who is inviſible with the eyes of my ſpirit; and certainly, I had theſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44694:23"/>
viſible eys given me as a ſigne or a ſhadow of the ſubſtance: <hi>Bleſſed therefore be the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which hath not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered me to ſtick in any thing below himſelf; but hath brought me through all the wiles and cunning deceits of Satan, and hath at length centured me in himſelf, and hath cauſed me to ſit down and reſt in his own boſome: Let there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our heavenly Father bee glorified, for this his great goodnes towards the Sonnes of men</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I have here digreſſed, I come againe therefore to tell you concerning this thing, that when the great day of judgement was upon me; this was one thing and a very great thing, for which I was judged of by the Lord, even that I had judged or paſt ſentence upon this pretious ſoule before the time, for the Lord of all men was at hand, and I ſhould have left all judgment unto him, but I was baſe and unworthy, and I judged thoſe things which I knew not: <hi>Bleſſed bee the Lord which hath not everlaſtingly cut me off for it; but hath accepted a ranſome in his beloved Jeſus; in</hi> Emanuel, <hi>God with us:</hi> that is, in himſelfe, even in the bowels of his owne love, manifeſted through fleſh: Now becauſe it hath been (as I have told you, ſo heavy a thing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44694:23"/>
upon me, I could not but acquaint you) as a forewarning, leaſt you alſo ſhould come into the ſame condition of torment by the like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion; and alſo that I might take ſhame to my ſelfe for my baſeneſſe and envy at Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Now that which I ſay, is the ſame with what I have already ſaid; that this Saint with many others, are riſen and come into my ſoule, accompanying my Saviour, and therefore if you ſee her, I ſhould deſire you to acquaint her with it, and ſhew her this paper that ſhee may ſee, how I have ſuffered for my perſecuting of her: but let her know, that now I am one in the body, with her; though I confeſſe I have beene exceeding vile and baſe: and when any have been ſpeaking of move light, or move ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall injoyments then I had, I would bid them be carefull and conſider what they did, and I would bring that mayd for an example to them, that they might ſee whereto ſhee was come, even, ſaid I, to deſtroy all; when indeed and in truth (as farre as I can ſee now) ſhee was come to the injoyment of all; this was the perſecuting ſpirit I was then of: nay deare friend I have not wondered ſince at her expreſſions, which I heard you ſay ſhee uſed; that was, why are you (ſaith ſhe) come to perſecute mee; you know that wee both
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:44694:24"/>
laughed at her and ſaid, was this the ſpirit that was upon her; but ſince I have conſidered it, and it was true enough; for fleſh muſt needs perſecute the ſpirit, and wee being fleſh came indeed to perſecure her; therefore, it was a true ſpirit of revelation that was upon her; though ſhe could not but beleeve our words, when we profeſſe to the contrary; but I confeſſe, I did not ſee you ſo apt to judge her as my ſelfe; and therefore it is juſt that I ſhould ſuffer in it, and you bee forewarned from it, for I did as much as in me lay, ſtrive to behead her, and lay her dead in the affections of my freinds, and all this was even for the teſtimony that ſhee bare of her Saviour; and therefore I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not thinke that the ſword muſt depart from my houſe, but that I muſt bee ſlaine in others affectiors, even as others have beene ſlaine in mine: I cannot paſſe by one thing conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in it, and that was this, I doe well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that even whilſt I ſpake againſt her, I was warned from within, that I ſhould take heed what I did; and I could never ſpeake of her, but I ſhould be ſmitten for it, and yet I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened not, <hi>but ruſhed into ſinne, as the Horſe into the battell;</hi> &amp; therefore I am willing now to take ſhame to my ſelfe, and have thus large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly written this to you, that you might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:44694:24"/>
it to whom you pleaſe, for indeed the goodneſſe of the Lord hath ſo overcome me, and the glory of my God is ſo riſen upon mee, that I care not, if all the world know my miſcarriages, I did not thinke to write ſo large to you, but my God ſo fils me, as I cannot tell how to leave; if you underſtand not my lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, I pray let Mr. <hi>G. C.</hi> helpe you, I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion not but hee may give you a ſight in it, to whom preſent my deare reſpects; alſo to all the reſt of my dear friends, tell them I am one in the ſpirit with them, and that I would have them carefull of judging; the good Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward you ſpirituall conſolations, for all your labour of love to me in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>I am your exceeding, loving, and as God ſhall make me, your faithfull friend to ſerve you.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="letter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:44694:25"/>
               <head>3. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Chriſtian friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur loving Father hath comforted me by your Letter; I exceedingly rejoyce in your condition, I ſee his very great power magnified in you, to make you thus willing to be at his diſpoſe: Its no ſmal matter for a ſoule to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it ſelfe. We have been a long time talking of <hi>ſelf-deniall,</hi> becauſe the letter of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath ſweetly ſpoken of it; but truly we have not known what it is, from the indwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of truth in us: I am ſure, thus much I finde, that it muſt be the death of the whol firſt man, that ſo the ſecond man may be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in righteouſnes; and truly, 'tis the mighty power of God muſt paſſe upon us, to raiſe us up to live thus in himſelf. I could willingly open to you, how I was brought (in that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that I am) into this life: It was by the ſight or viſion of God himſelf. For as I was one day carried forth by him to ſpeake ſome thing to another, as he ſpake in me; I had this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44694:25"/>
wonderfull Viſion that <hi>confounded</hi> me, and threw me to the ground before it, for it was no leſſe then <hi>infiniteneſſe</hi> it ſelf that beheld me, and at laſt made mee to behold it: but this ſight of God did ſo aſtoniſh me, it deſtroyed and wrought ſuch an utter death to my ſelfe, and to every thing below or beſides him, (I mean things that appear to be;) that truly I may ſay, <hi>I had no ſpirit of a man left in me;</hi> but I ſat before him as a meer paſſive appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. Then I felt the ſpirit of life from above enter into me again, <hi>and carried me forth to act where, when, and how it pleaſed;</hi> Now came I to be what he would have me, and never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>It was not long ſince, that I ſhould have been much troubled, to be called hither and thither, and to act the part of ſuch or ſuch a one; No, the reaſonable man indeed was not dead yet in me, <hi>but now the Lord ſo ſlew it,</hi> that I cryed out; <hi>Here am I Lord, ſend me, for I am no more my ſelf now, nor to act for my ſelf, but for the Lord:</hi> And I wondred ſtill, why the fleſh in the ordinary appearnce of it, did remain? I mean, this outward form or veſſel, that held the treaſure; for indeed, I thought when the Apoſtle ſpake of a <hi>change,</hi> that it had been the <hi>changing</hi> of the outward
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:44694:26"/>
forme; but this day came upon me unawars: However, I doe not ſay, the outward <hi>form</hi> ſhal not be <hi>changed:</hi> let it be as it pleaſeth him, <hi>my glory lies within the Vaile;</hi> I am not called ſo much to talk or judge of things without, I am to judge of things within me. Thoſe things that I have taſted, ſeen and handled, I declare unto you; for the diſpenſation of truth is upon me: and I would not now ſpeak any thing, or doe any thing, but as he ſpeaks in me, and does in me; <hi>for its no more I now, but the Lord:</hi> I, indeed have been ſomething in mans day, and I deſired to be and to ſpeak; but that day is paſt, its come into judgement, weighed in the ballance of the Sanctuary, and found too light. <hi>The day of the Lord onely is now upon me;</hi> and here I deſire to be perfected.</p>
               <p>But I will yet goe a little further, and ſhew you the workings of God upon me, and in me: It was ſo, that before God ſo wonderfully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to me; <hi>I had exceeding working in my ſpirit, and drawing to come up and ſerve the Lord in a more ſpirituall adminiſtration;</hi> and ſcriptures were ſtill opened to me, in a new and ſtrange way; ſtill tending to that ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all enjoyment of God, which then was in mine eye, and now have. At laſt there was an extraordinary expectation begotten in me;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44694:26"/>
and I waited for my <hi>eſtabliſhment</hi> in the <hi>ſpirit;</hi> though I did yet appear in the <hi>fleſh:</hi> but againſt this, there were great fightings between the two <hi>powers,</hi> both from within me, and alſo from <hi>friends</hi> without: yet there was in mee, even in the darkeſt time, a ſecret <hi>hope;</hi> even beyond <hi>hope,</hi> that I ſhould enjoy it, <hi>and my eye was unto him who hath now ſaved me:</hi> but here I was brought to lye down in his will, even without it; and though I never ſhould have felt it, yet in this <hi>beliefe,</hi> could I have laid down my life, and have dyed. That there was ſuch a time appointed for the people of God; and that they ſhould ſurely have ſuch a glory, though they appeared and lived upon earth; for the Lord hath ſaid, <hi>The taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of God ſhould be with men; and he would raigne for ever and ever.</hi> But the day before this glory came unto me; I had this word ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrongly ſet home upon me, <hi>Wee ſhall not all ſleep, but be changed:</hi> And truly as the time drew neer, <hi>I had ſuch ſtrong workings of ſpirit, that I could expect no other indeed;</hi> and I did expect it, and withall look't with what body I ſhould come; for I was thinking (as I told you before) that this outward form muſt be done away, when God came to <hi>change</hi> us; but when I ſaw it ſtill remain, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44694:27"/>
I ſo wonderfully beheld God, I was taken with admiration; yet did I ſtill expect, that ſure it would anone goe a way, for I thought it impoſſible, that I ſhould look conſtantly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this <hi>glory,</hi> and yet remain upon the earth; for indeed though I expected much, yet this ſight was farre beyond my expectation. Now I felt the fleſhly part within me flie a way at his preſence, <hi>and Death and Hell were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; I heard ſentence given againſt the enemy of all our peace,</hi> and he ran a way; <hi>I felt him caſt out, and in the morning I could ſing a ſong over him:</hi> For his head I found, was turned into the waters, yet ſtill this outward body did not moulder a way. At laſt it was given mee from him that ſhewed me theſe things to aske, (for indeed, I was not able till it was given me) and I asked and ſaid; <hi>O Lord God, why have I fleſh upon me, and ſee thee in this glorious manner?</hi> (for <hi>Infiniteneſſe</hi> it ſelf looked upon me, and I looked upon it:) <hi>Can any man ſee thee (I ſaid) and live?</hi> It was anſwered me againe: <hi>Thou art not alive; I have ſlain thee: No man indeed can ſee mee and live; but as a man thou art dead, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhalt live more, as a man; but the ſonne of God can ſee mee: Thou ſhall live as the ſon of God, and ſo thou ſhalt ſee me:</hi> But I ſaid;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44694:27"/>
                  <hi>O Lord, Why am I not preſently diſſolved by this Infinite glory that now ſo openly beholds me? Why have I fleſh upon me in the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of it?</hi> It was anſwered; <hi>Thou haſt brethren in the fleſh, therefore haſt thou fleſh upon thee, becauſe thou muſt carry them a teſtimony of what thou haſt ſeen of me: but look for no glory in the fleſh, but ſufferings and perſeeutions for thy glory lyes within all fleſh, and accordingly I accepted of it, becauſe it was the fathers will, and for no other cauſe.</hi> It was alſo manifeſted to me, that while they were perſecuting me, I ſhould be inwardly filled with the glory of God, and triumph o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all their cruelty, though I might for this teſtimony ſuffer as <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> did upon the Croſs. I ſhould bee willing, in the will of God, to ſee your face; however this I am ſure, that when the Lord brings forth his own righteouſnes upon you, you cannot be ſilent to your own bowels, and that indeed I am; for I am not as to my own particular any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but am fallen into the Church, and there I ſee my ſelf to have a moſt glorious reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: I was afraid once indeed to looſe my life; but I never had ſo much glory as now I finde in the body: Oh, how true is that word; <hi>Every one that will ſave his life ſhall looſe it,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44694:28"/>
but he that looſeth his life for my name ſake ſhall find it:</hi> The Lord of heaven and earth give men to ſee their glory in union, and then they will never ſtand ſo much as they doe upon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions; did they ſee their <hi>reſurrection</hi> in the body, (and knew what this body is, they could not ſo account of any particular appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances; but they ſhould ſee themſelves al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes alive: and becauſe he lives, therefore they ſhould live alſo; for if they would ceaſe to live in their own life, they ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected and live in the life of God: But the truth is, the word (<hi>Body</hi>) ſtumbles them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not wholly yet brought off from looking upon things as they appear; for, hence hath flowen all our imaginary worſhip: but when <hi>Chriſt</hi> is again formed in us, then he and we by him, ſhall not judge according to the hearing of the ear, nor the ſight of the eye; <hi>but righteous judgement:</hi> Therefore <hi>the filth of the daughter of</hi> Sion (or all thoſe evils and miſtakes which now poſſeſſe us) <hi>is ſaid to be purged away by a ſpirit of judgment, as well as by a ſpirit of burning:</hi> For it muſt be firſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before it can be burned; and truly I doe in ſom meaſure ſee what that Scripture ſpeaks off.</p>
               <p>After death comes judgement; for <hi>I</hi> am ſure that ſince <hi>I</hi> had this death, and ſince my
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:44694:28"/>
ſoule was ſeparated from my body, <hi>I</hi> have been judged for things done in the body; that is, while <hi>I</hi> lived in the body; for I knew a time when I lived in this body, and <hi>I</hi> know now what it is to live out of the body, and yet appear in the body; for that is the great miſtake: <hi>the body that appears to be, is not the body:</hi> The ſcripture ſaith, <hi>Its ſown a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, but raiſed a ſpirituall body:</hi> and men not knowing what to make of this ſpirituall body, conceive it to be ſo many diſtinct per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall appearances as have deceaſed ſince the world firſt began: <hi>but the Lord in his time will ſhew them what this ſpirituall body is, and then they will better judge of it:</hi> but <hi>I</hi> am ſure we without them, or they without us are not perfect; for though <hi>I</hi> have ſeen all theſe things accompliſhed upon me, in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular body; yet <hi>I</hi> ſee that it is but as in a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, which hath reference to the whole; therefore am <hi>I</hi> weak with them that are weak, and ſtong with thoſe that are ſtrong, and my glory lyes ſtill in the body. Never do <hi>I</hi> look for perfection more in one particular appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance but to be perfect in the whole: <hi>I am no more my own, but every ones, and every one is mine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dear Soul,</hi> the Lord of all our mercy ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44694:29"/>
and keep you ſafe, under all thoſe ſtorms which are now breaking in upon us; <hi>I</hi> hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and heartily thank you for your ſweet counſell in looking for tryall: it is that which my heavenly father hath warned me to look for. <hi>I</hi> leave you to his bowels and boſome, in whom <hi>I</hi> reſt;</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>I am, Your endeared friend to ſerve God in you.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="letter">
               <head>4. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Soule,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y heart ſalutes thee, and every budding forth of God in the <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine myſtery:</hi> Oh, my ſpirit ſits inthron'd, and glories in the top of every being, and though all the buildings in the world ſhake, I ſhal not come down to ſave any of the furniture of this darke <hi>Fabrick.</hi> All images are with me (<hi>my deareſt</hi>) though ſet in a frame of weakneſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The eye of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44694:29"/>
hath encloſ'd them all, and though its twinklings fold them up in night: and though the back-parts of <hi>God</hi> obſcures this earth, and is a veile between it and the high-noone of the <hi>God-head;</hi> yet this is but a ſhadow wherein <hi>Divinity</hi> hides it ſelfe, which ſhall fly away, and diſappeare, with the outward dreſſe of this <hi>Creation:</hi> When all deformed <hi>Shapes, Vizards</hi> and <hi>Pictures</hi> ſhall ſuffer loſſe; then the preſent blackneſſe (which is the habitation of <hi>Dogs</hi> and <hi>Devils</hi>) ſhall bee chas'd into outward darkneſſe, but the comli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (which all this while hath lyen diſguiſed under that beggerly appearance and loathſome outwardneſſe) ſhall ſpring forth in a glorious ray of that bright <hi>morning Starre</hi> which ſhall viſit us from on high, bringing glad tydings upon its <hi>Angel-wing</hi> of life and immortal lity.</p>
               <p>That the ſweet <hi>Emmanuel</hi> born in the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage of our own natures. I am commanded to ſpeake thus much unto thee (<hi>my Dear breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>) though my <hi>ſpirit</hi> rejoyceth to finde-thee already reeling with new wine; bathing in that brimfull unction which yet cannot runne over its boundleſſe circle, and ſhall overflow all the world beſides; <hi>They ſhall all know God, and all be cloathed with the divine perſon
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44694:30"/>
of Chriſt: The water of life ſhall ſpring up in you all, and every Creature heald of its diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, when righteouſneſſe ſhall ſpring forth of the earth, and the heavens ſhall hear the voyce of the earth, and drop down fatneſſe upon them.</hi> The <hi>Tree of Life</hi> ſhall have its <hi>root</hi> within us, ſprouting forth through its quiet <hi>Sap</hi> into its glorious figure and life; a <hi>Branch,</hi> a <hi>Leafe</hi> thereof reducing every parcell of <hi>Corruption</hi> and cloathing that upon with <hi>ſpirit</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortallity</hi> which before was muffled up in <hi>ſinne</hi> and <hi>wrath,</hi> in <hi>paine</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My deareſt, I am taken off in haſte and have onely leyſure to bleſſe thee for thy laſt, which adminiſtred ſo much glory to my <hi>ſpirit;</hi> live ſtill happily my dear ſelfe in the ripe <hi>Navell</hi> of <hi>Divinity</hi> and let me ſee thee every moment in the divine <hi>Principle</hi> of glory whither the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> is riſen before and hath call'd up himſelfe out of the fleſh of,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. M.</signed>
Salvation-Bulwarks in the eternall Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath with out the number of a man.</closer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="letter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:44694:30"/>
               <head>5. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Mine in the Lord</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE preſent diſpoſings of God towards me are very ſweet and precious, my ſoule being ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed daily to the <hi>Lords</hi> will in all things: I ſee daily, that the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> deſignes is to ſweeten all conditions to me by the beames of his owne preſence.</p>
               <p>Truly in the Lord theirs nothing comes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe to me, but I am able to welcome every diſpoſe of providence; <hi>death, ſorrow</hi> and <hi>miſery</hi> in the <hi>Lord,</hi> are ſo familiar to me, that <hi>I</hi> know not how to bee without them; my ſoule longs after affliction, becauſe now the ſting of miſery is gone, and it is my delight to play with it; <hi>I</hi> thinke <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſtarve with hunger, but that my own wants daily ſupply me; ſweet ſoule, <hi>God</hi> is teaching me to ſee <hi>light</hi> in <hi>darkneſſe, good</hi> in <hi>evill,</hi> to eat upon the <hi>eater,</hi> and receive <hi>ſweetneſſe</hi> from the ſtrong, to behold a happy harmony in all contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:44694:31"/>
                  <hi>I ſhall ſhortly bee with you, now I am not from you; but reſt in thy boſome.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>The Lord that ſpirit, in the fleſh.</closer>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="letter">
               <head>6. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sweet and pure Spirit,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N divine progreſſe, I continually meet thee, with a heart drawn out: <hi>I alwayes ſalute thee,</hi> I can be no where, doe nothing, but thou art ſtill with mee; <hi>In thy life I live, in thy light I ſee, by thy power I ſtand;</hi> I am nothing but in thee, and thou the ſame without mee; my fulneſſe is thy treaſure, and thy treaſure is my fulneſſe; all that I have, I receive from thee, and yet what thou giveſt me is nothing but my own, and ſo was from eternity. I was with thee from the beginning, and thy begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was in my eternity; I was with thee when thou didſt inhabite darkneſſe, thy darkneſſe was my ſecret place, my ſecret
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:44694:31"/>
place was thy darknes; when the curs &amp; enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the old creation lay upon me, thy power upheld me, this power was mine own, for it was no robbery for me to be equall with thee, my form vailed thy glory, yet it was my glory and thy form. Thus thou for me, and I in thee have borne the ſinne and curſe of of the old world; (born it I ſay) into a land of forgetfulneſſe, which have forgotten and forgiven all tranſgreſſion: and thus in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled and ſweet union, thou remaineſt my fulneſſe, and I reſt thy happineſſe: Though in the fleſh, I ſubſcribe my ſelfe diſtant by the name of—</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From the Head-quarters of Divine Majeſty, <date>this laſt Lords-day, in the year of Jubile.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="letter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:44694:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>7. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome glimmerings preſented, to the <hi>children of love,</hi> clothed with darkneſſe, bewilderneſſed in their ſpirits, paſſing through the fiery tryall, or crucifyings of fleſh, or things of the firſt <hi>Creation,</hi> unto the the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> of reſt, or to a more higher, fuller, and excellent glory.</p>
               <p>Firſt conſidering the ſeverall <hi>diſpenſations</hi> of the eternall God: how hee hath ſeverall wayes and in divers manners, made out him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to a creature, as <hi>Geneſis Chap.</hi> I. and 2. the <hi>law,</hi> or <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> of the firſt creation, in which God had communion with man, and man with God, yet rather with a <hi>Creator,</hi> then with a <hi>Father,</hi> and that in the outward court, or firſt <hi>creation,</hi> not in the inmoſt, or holieſt; and <hi>Paradice</hi> it ſelfe being but an image, of the excellency, of this firſt <hi>Creation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Man being fallen, or deprived of this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, which was accompliſhed through the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:44694:32"/>
temptation of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> or <hi>fleſhly wiſdome,</hi> or the eſpouſals of the woman, or weakneſſe of this <hi>creation,</hi> there was the firſt <hi>law</hi> of righteouſneſſe, preſented in a new miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of letter by <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>tables of ſtone</hi> from <hi>God;</hi> in which the firſt glory or perfection and excellency, was miniſtred to man in his fallen and apoſtated condition, and becauſe the <hi>law,</hi> or firſt <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> was weake through the <hi>fleſh,</hi> after the departing of the power ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting, or unanſwerableneſſe, of the apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed ſtate, to the firſt uprightneſſe there was given (or God appearing to the refreſhing and comforting of the <hi>creature</hi>) an adminiſtratiou of <hi>Angels,</hi> by <hi>viſions</hi> and <hi>dreams,</hi> as alſo a Prieſt-hood with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, Ceremonies, Tabernacle, Temple,</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> ſpeaking forth immediate revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by which man might have acceſſe to God and ſpeake with him, but in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward court, or through the fleſh, or of this <hi>creation,</hi> though he filled theſe with another glory, a higher and more excellenter diſcovery of his love in the promiſed <hi>ſeed:</hi> the ſubſtance and excellency of that, with all the former were but ſhadowes.</p>
               <p>There was another miniſtration added of <hi>war,</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>tryals, crucifyings,</hi> or
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:44694:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>baptiſmes</hi> in the fleſh as flying before <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oh</hi> and following a cloud of fire and black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, through or betwixt the wales of b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing waves, in terror and feare, the long marching through a <hi>wilderneſſe,</hi> by the waters of <hi>Meriba,</hi> and <hi>rock of ſtrife,</hi> skirmiſhing with <hi>Amalekites,</hi> by the terrour of <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> cutting their way through <hi>Ogg</hi> King of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhan,</hi> and paſſing through the dividings of <hi>Jordan</hi> into <hi>Canaan,</hi> another miniſtration was given of <hi>Canaanites</hi> in the land, warre with the <hi>Nations,</hi> captivity, deſtruction of the <hi>Temple,</hi> Gods departing, the apoſtacy over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpreading, or God gathering up that glory which appeared in the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> and <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and that of <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Prophet,</hi> ceaſing; there then followed a night of darkneſſe or an apoſtaſie upon all that adminiſtration, and when God no longer filled the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> with a cloud, and the <hi>Temple</hi> with glory, they became a place of ſolitaryneſſe or deſolation, as all other miniſtrations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and places for the <hi>Satire</hi> and the <hi>Scrich-Owle</hi> to dwell, and ſing in, that is, for the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> or <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> or of <hi>Iniquity</hi> to poſſeſſe, and act in.</p>
               <p>Another miniſtration ſomewhat clearer and briter then that of the <hi>Law;</hi> and that was of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:44694:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>John,</hi> as in <hi>Matthew, A greater had not riſſen, he was a burning and ſhining light,</hi> as Luke 1. <hi>the Law and Prophets were till</hi> John, <hi>he was the Prophet of the higheſt,</hi> in reſpect of what went before, <hi>and was ſent to make Chriſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to Saints, by word and water,</hi> and this was a miniſtration in order to one more ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, the one miniſtration was to decreaſe, the other to increaſe, and that of fire or of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, was to burne up that of water or of fleſh, or that which conſiſted of things of this <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another and more glorious miniſtration was that appearance of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or the Goſpel in fleſh, or glad tydings manifeſted to ſinners, or the apoſtatiſed <hi>creation, Heb.</hi> 1. or God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and familiareſt rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this <hi>creation</hi> to man, even in fleſh in which hee taught, and did miracles, and was circumciſed, and baptized, and acted to fulfill all righteouſneſſe, in which there was a cleare draught of that miniſtration of gifts and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, which was as perfect as the firſt <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in its glory, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> higher and nearer to God comming forth in nearer relation of an <hi>Emmanuel</hi> or God with us. Another Adminiſtration alſo of Chriſt in the fleſh of Saints, <hi>Col. 1. 27. Chriſt in you the hope of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:44694:34"/>
glory,</hi> and that by graces, and operations, and fruits of <hi>ſpirit,</hi> as of <hi>faith, repentance, love, ſelfe-denyall, humiliation, meekneſſe,</hi> alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible gifts of ſpirit, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſpeake with tongues, workmiracles and act infallibly &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, even the height of the glorious Goſpel, or God ſhining in the face of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Now the ſpirit of God foreſeeing Gods purpoſe, to leave this miniſtration of Goſpel glory to the <hi>world,</hi> (or <hi>fleſh,</hi> or <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi>) and to bring a night of darkneſſe upon all the day and brightneſſe of his Sunne; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of a departing firſt before the man of ſinne, fleſhly wiſdome, or Antichriſt, could be revealed, or Gods departing from that Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration as hee did from the Tabernacle and Temple, and whilſt <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> or the power of the <hi>fleſh,</hi> or the <hi>ſpirt</hi> of <hi>iniquity</hi> reigns in the chriſtian world, or amongſt ſuch as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe a <hi>Chriſt,</hi> all this while the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>glory</hi> or <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in ſpirit is crucified in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Sodom, Aegypt,</hi> or <hi>Babylon,</hi> or the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the fleſh, and the powers of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; ſo that there is no mention of any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration of the firſt miniſtry of gifts and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances which was in the Apoſtles dayes: but is the ſtate and perſecution of the <hi>Lord
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:44694:34"/>
Jeſus</hi> in ſpirit, and all thoſe appearances of the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> in many glorious <hi>Saints</hi> in perticular ages, was but the appearance of him who is that faithfull and true witneſſe, or the propheſings of ſpirit in ſack-cloath, againſt the power of the man of ſinne, and were but drops of the Vials, ſounding of the Trumpet, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Seales before the battell of the great day, when God ſhall appeare in flames of ſpirit and glory againſt and to confound Antichriſt, or fleſhly powers, or things of this <hi>creation.</hi> So that there is not (as <hi>I</hi> know of at preſent) any word in all the Scriptures, that the firſt miniſtry by gifts and ordinances, ſhall in any meaſure be continued or reſtored, in whole or in part. As if that were the great worke the Lord intended, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſet up the former mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, or the reſtoring ſome legall ordinances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as if all the glory of the laſt times ſhould be the bringing theſe, or recovering them out of the hands of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> that is, not my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent apprehenſions: but that the next miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wil be the fiery tryal, or a ſtate and power of God, put forth upon the ſeverall admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations that Chriſtians are under, in order to higher diſcoveries of God, which will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce torment in the fleſh (with blackneſſe, and darkneſſe, and tempeſt) or upon fleſhly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:44694:35"/>
wiſdome, and powers, or things of this <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. viz.</hi> in ſome, in paſſing from legall mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations to a more evangelicall, of grace and love; there will bee torment and tempeſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that adminiſtration or ſelfe righteouſneſſe in the conſumption thereof.</p>
               <p>In that more Goſpel ſtate of a Chriſtian, whereby he injoyes God in graces, gifts and contemplations, with ſweet taſtes and imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of divine glory; there will bee a fiery try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, or the clouds of fire and darkneſſe, or cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyings in the fleſh and upon that miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of gifts and graces, inſomuch that there will bee a ſcorching up of the ſtreames, or of <hi>Euphrates,</hi> &amp; the pleaſant vallies turned into a parched wilderneſſe, and all in order to a more higher, fuller and excellenter glory; this is propheſied of in the Scripture, <hi>The Sunne ſhall bee turned into darkneſſe and the Moone into blood, before that great and notable day of the Lord come;</hi> that is not onely the Lord Jeſus will be darkneſſe unto the world (which I deny not) but all that which was the glory, and light of a Chriſtian, and high-way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, his Sunne, Moone, and Starres ſhall be darkned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> before that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table day or that more excellent revelation of God in glory, and 1 <hi>Pet. 3. 10. The heavens
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:44694:35"/>
ſhall paſſe away with a great noiſe; and the Element ſhall melt with fervent heat, and the earth with the works that are therein ſhall be burnt up:</hi> which is not onely at the laſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but upon perticular adminiſtration, which is figured out in the heavens, earth and elements; or thoſe more, or leſſe glorious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations: and the fire ſhall try every mans work, of what ſort it is; 1 Cor. 3. 13. 15. And as <hi>Chriſt</hi> crucified all that glorious adminiſtration in the fleſh, in which he was, and it all dyed to a more glorious life: ſo eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſtian, is to take up his croſſe, or to bring his higheſt and cheifeſt adminiſtrations to this croſſe, and to leave them all crucified, to more higher, &amp; excellenter diſcoveries: and this is the knowledge of <hi>Chriſt</hi> crucified: now many Chriſtians who are ſadded, darkned, and in much tribulation, as to the adminiſtration they are under; and in looking into the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, ſeeing nothing but mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> with blackneſſe, and darknes, and tempeſt: they take it for deſertions, and withdrawings of God, when as indeed, it is the preſence of God, darkning, withering, and conſuming ſuch adminiſtrations and the bringing in a more fuller and tranſcendent glory.</p>
               <p>The next miniſtration will be the appearing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:44694:36"/>
of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in brightneſſe and glory of <hi>Spirit,</hi> deſtroying <hi>Antichriſt</hi> with the ſpirit of his mouth, and brightnes of his comming; this ſhall be a glory without Sun, or Moon, or Star, or any ſuch low appearance, as gift or ordinance: but the Lord ſhall be there everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting light, and God the glory, and light ſhall cover the earth, as waters cover the Sea, that is it ſhall not ſparkle, or be in bright beams, as in a Gift or Ordinance; but it ſhall ſlow out from the Lord ſwallowing up and overflowing all earthly adminiſtrations, that expectation of him in externall admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations as Gifts or Ordinances, &amp;c. is but to expect <hi>Chriſt</hi> in a fleſhly way or appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and not as he is in his own height, ſpirit, and glory in himſelfe, in his Saints, <hi>their ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and hope of glory, Col.</hi> 1. 27. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is that which is to be expected, an eſtate of <hi>ſpirit, love, meeknes, ſelf-denyall, overcoming evill with good, conquering by receiving in the wrath and enmity of the world, into which eſtate God will gather up his people by times and degrees, from all worldy and fleſhly intereſts and ingagements, wherein they ſhall be carried up into a more full injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, and conformity to Chriſt in all his ſufferings, death, and reſurrection, where
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:44694:36"/>
God will be to all his, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> glorified, as broad ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and ſtreams, where ſhall goe no Ship with ſailes, nor Gally with Ores.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then it ſhall be, as much apoſtacy, in the Saints to go back, to the firſt miniſtery of the Goſpel times, or firſt patterne which was the firſt diſcovery of that myſtery, hid from ages, as would have been in them in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles dayes to have gone back to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Tabernacle, Temple, and Prieſt-hood, &amp;c. out of which God had departed, as he alſo hath, out of theſe late adminiſtrations.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Furnell.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="letter">
               <head>8. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Loving Cozen,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Early and much beloved, there is ſome content in nature, that you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in the fleſh with me, and are yet an appearance of God upon the Earth, for I confeſſe I have none ſo neere my
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:44694:37"/>
heart as you, of a fleſhly beeing in the world; therefore, I have been affected with the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Lord, that hath ſpared you, that I might not have ſorrow upon ſorrow; my ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter being removed, yet have I more ſweet joy and content in underſtanding that you are in the fellowſhip of the Spirit, growing forward through al the dark ſhadows of ſeeming glory, into the ſubſtance which is reall glory; for in that you ſay, you ſee God is all, and doth all: I queſtion not, but you underſtand that all things below him are but ſhaddows of him; yea, Chriſt himſelf in his fleſhly appearance was but a form of God which appeared to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer our diſtance from God; for wee being departed from him by experiencing the <hi>Tree of Knowledge, of Good and Evill,</hi> of which food, I hope, we have our fill now, God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending to redeem us from this, by the way of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who was appointed of God to bring us unto God, not to himſelf as he was <hi>Chriſt,</hi> beeing but an appearance of God, not the Father himſelf: Therefore if we ſhould ſit down with <hi>Chriſt</hi> (being come to him) and proceed no further, we are not brought by him to the Father; And the will of God is <hi>that we be co-heires and joint heires together with him, till we know that the Father and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:44694:37"/>
the Son are in one, and we one with the Father as the Son.</hi> For I believe that God, even the Son of God, doth dwell in us, even the ſame that dwelt in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> and I am waiting when that heavenly <hi>Image</hi> ſhall as plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, as the <hi>Image</hi> of the earthly hath appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, for we ſhal ſee his face, and his name ſhall be upon our foreheads.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deere Cozen,</hi> ſince I received your letter, I have ſeen you in a Viſion, and ſo was it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to me, that I underſtand, that you have or ſhall bring forth the man Childe even Chriſt to open veiw; for which you muſt die and be buried: I mean you ſhall appear to ſome as one dead to truth and God, and alive to errour: and ſo you ſhall be as one dead and put into a grave of darknes and ſilence; yet fear not, for <hi>I</hi> have proved that the day of death is better then the day of Birth; <hi>And that by death, Chriſt brought to light life and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality: Remember alſo Chriſt was put to death in the fleſh, and was alive to God, his fleſh was as pure and honourable as even ours was: yet by the eternall Spirit within, it was offered a Spirituall Sacrifice to God, whileſt the dark apprehenſions of men conclude that he ſuffered as a blaſphemer: therefore arm your ſelf with the ſame minde always expecting we ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:44694:38"/>
riſe with him, as we ſuffer together with him; for indeed we are but one in life and death, And he is the reſurrection and the life, even Chriſt in us, who is riſing in me, and either is or will riſe in you. And when he doth appear we ſhall appear with him.</hi> I pray you, <hi>deare Cozen,</hi> as often as conveniently you may, let me hear from you (<hi>I</hi> would not burden you.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="letter">
               <head>9. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Deare Siſter,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ITH the reſt of my fellow heires in the Son-ſhip, in this unity of Truth and Love I ſalute you; I thanke you for appointing a freind to relate to mee your eſtate in the things of God, of whom I received information to much content, having for a long time before had great deſire to underſtand your condition, and am now fully ſatisfied in it, as for the dealings of the Lord with me, I am free to give you ſome account; I am indeed in the judgement of thoſe to whom the day of judgement is not
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:44694:38"/>
yet come, accounted and termed an <hi>Heretique,</hi> but in the light and truth of God, a <hi>Co-heire</hi> with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> being annointed with the ſame oyle of gladneſſe, which is indeed joy to the ſpirit and as marrow to the bones; and a perpetual light of truth in certainty and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and in ſuch fulneſſe already that he beares witneſſe to himſelfe in others that it is hee; and <hi>fulneſſe of wiſdome</hi> and might to anſwer all the occaſions; that he is pleaſed to preſent himſelfe to me and magnify himſelfe in mee: as for the Scripture it is much unſealed, and I <hi>have ſweet ſellow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſip in that one ſpirit that throdgbout all ages declared the Father &amp; the Son;</hi> as for the miniſtry of Angels I know it, having for a long time beene under it, but of late have had knowing, underſtanding of it, and fellowſhip with underſtanding among them; truly my deare companions, our God that ſaveth us is perfect and ſo is his ſalvation, which when we ſhall be by him circumciſed in heart which is the taking away <hi>the fleſhly vaile and the face of the covering that is ſpread over all Nations, Iſaiah</hi> 25. then ſhall wee ſee and with joy poſſeſſe together that it is the ſame ſtrong one that prepareth us and júdgeth darkneſſe; I ſpeake not this as if dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe were contrary to this mighty God, for in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:44694:39"/>
his light it is that hee is at unity with all the workes of wonder which hee brings forth; <hi>darkneſſe is not ſo to him,</hi> for <hi>the darkneſſe lo him is as cleare as the noon-day;</hi> that is, hee ſeeth as fully and poſſeth as contentedly his will in the darkneſſe as in the light, and when wee are taken into that eternall light, we ſhall ſee our God is as rich and wonderfull in the deeps of darkneſſe as in the cleareſt light, for in the unity of the ſpirit it is eaſily diſcerned, that <hi>God is one in all,</hi> though different in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming forth; for as in a garden, the ſeverall colours of flowers make the moſt glorious appearance, even ſo light and darkneſſe are the two generall treaſures of the Almighty, in both which hee is infinite and wonderfull; and as hee pleaſeth to take us into either of theſe, ſo it is to make himſelfe known in his unſearchable greatneſſe, as in <hi>Iſay</hi> he ſayth, <hi>Hee will give unto us the hidden treaſures of darkneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Malachi</hi> ſayth, <hi>that the Sunne of Righteouſneſſe ſhall ariſe upon us.</hi> Both which Scriptures import to me, that God himſelfe in his apperance to us is both the treaſures of darkneſſe, and the Sunne of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe; and it is all one to me whether hee take me with him into the heights above or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the depths beneath, for wee are ever toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:44694:39"/>
and I poſſeſſe the fulfilling of that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which ſayth, <hi>where I am there ſhall my Servant bee;</hi> ſo that when God my excellency will appeare in the externall <hi>creation,</hi> which is a thick vail, and the inviſible one much hid in it, yet I have ſweet diſcerning of him and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with him there; and when hee takes me into the <hi>deeps of darknes,</hi> God my glory is with me, and we either ſee us one or lie down in one: and when hee will aſcend into the higheſt Heavens, he carrieth me up along with him. What is all this? but the manifeſtation that his dwelling place is large and deepe, and that hee himſelfe is the one infiniteneſſe. The fulneſſe that filleth all in all things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="letter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:44694:40"/>
               <head>10. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Received yours, which brings mee the ſtate of affaires then in agitation, between the Parliament and Army; you ſend mee what they beſt approve of, and what they dare not owne: No wonder if ſome good men are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this <hi>dilemma;</hi> many I know are almoſt broken betweene thoſe principles (they call) of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and thoſe of <hi>God:</hi> the firſt (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging man to be compounded of two natures, earth and heaven, light and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:) breake the actions into ſeverall ſtreames, as if of two and not one perſon. It is our miſery and the ſadneſſe of our ſpirits that we are held in theſe chaines of earth and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that wee are fetterd in theſe priſons of mortality and are not free in all things to act like our ſelves, as ſprung from a divine Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as born of a nobler ſeed, and putting forth the ſtrength and power of the divine nature, in actions purely and ſimply ſpirituall: But if
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:44694:40"/>
this light ſhine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not upon our ſpirits in its <hi>Meridian-glory,</hi> let us wait till the Sunne ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, let us not walke in the paths of darkneſſe, according to the principle and ſpirit of this world: There is glorious light in the eaſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, the Mountaine tops beginne to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it. When I looke upon the world and ſurvay the <hi>actions of men;</hi> when I conſider the intereſts and principles of the moſt, the fleſhly toylings and ſtruglings of the ſpirits of the worlds reformers; I cannot but ſee much <hi>weakneſſe and darkneſſe,</hi> generating poore and ſpiritleſſe deſignes, which rend, and teare, and never bind up the breaches of a Kingdome. 'Tis true, the body politicke (as you write) was deſperately ſicke, and a deſperate diſeaſe muſt have a deſperate cure; but conſider the nature of the diſeaſe, and then judge of the meanes to cure it: All the properties of hell and darknes, all the ſuperfluities of folly and vanity, all the miſts of errour and ſuperſtition had formd themſelves into a body of <hi>corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and ſo aſſaulted and poſseſsed the vitall parts both of Church and State, ſeizing the heart and ſpirits of <hi>government</hi> and <hi>religion;</hi> the ſoule of both were fled, there remained little but a poore carkaſs, a painted <hi>image,</hi> a ſpiritleſs <hi>form,</hi> without any motion, but artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:44694:41"/>
and violent: But tell me what is the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick to cure this <hi>Lethargy?</hi> Parliament and People, Church and State, Soul and Body were languiſhing with this ſickneſs: <hi>A ſpirit of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation begins to worke:</hi> The faint breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the ſpirit of life, puts ſome upon indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to undertake the cure: ſome (according to the ſpirit that acted them) mixt ingredients, earthly and carnall (ignorant <hi>Empiricks,</hi> who knew not the nature of the diſeaſe or cure) others ranſacke the bowels of nature and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſtudy the practiſes and preſcriptions of the old <hi>Heroe's</hi> of the world, the Heathen Conquerers and reformers of Nations; and yet never riſe ſo high, either in magnanimity or greatneſſe of ſpirit, to doe good in their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, and command themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: Some ſearch deeper and throw into this compoſition, ſome graines of ſpirit, and <hi>quinteſſences,</hi> of a higher extract, purified and ſublimd into a nobler eſſence. But tell mee is this mixture like to reſtore life to a dying and languiſhing <hi>Nation,</hi> to a darke and formall <hi>Church?</hi> Could wee get the rareſt drugs the world affords? Could we ſearch the earth to its center, and diſcover the occult qualities of all its minerals and wonders? Can this reach the ſome and ſpirit of one man, much leſſe a
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:44694:41"/>
whole kingdome? What though ſome grains of ſpirit are in one compoſition, is it not load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with thick clay, overcome by the predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy of contrary qualities? The <hi>diſtemper of this Nation ſprings</hi> from our living in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world, then our own, in a corrupted aire: a contagious climate; in vaſſalage and ſlavery to theſe bodies of fleſh, to this lower element of the world, to the Prince of darkneſſe: Men created in the Image of God, have uncloath'd themſelves of that glory, and now wander in the ſhapes of <hi>Wolves</hi> and <hi>Beaſts of prey;</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their ſoules and ſpirits ſprung from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, they transforme themſelves into the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of the <hi>elementary-creatures:</hi> What are warres, confuſions, and diſorders, but the act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings forth this brutiſh ſpirit in tearing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring our fellow <hi>creatures? Fightings and diviſions ſpring from the jarring, diſcordant qualities in the mindes of men,</hi> who have loſt the ſpirit of ſweetneſs, union and peace, which breaths forth nothing but love &amp; joy, and keeps the whole body in an harmonious unity. Is this unity to be recovered by diviſions? Tis true, by ſuch a diviſion as this it is, by ſeperating truth from errour, light from darkneſs, the purer from the groſser parts: This is by a ſpirit of burning and by a power above the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:44694:42"/>
ſtrength of man. Who muſt be the reformers of the world? who muſt build the Lord a Temple, a glorious Temple both in Church and State? Not thoſe who are ſtaind with bloud, and act by a ſpirit of wrath and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: The Lord tels <hi>David,</hi> 1 Chron. 22. 8. <hi>Thou haſt ſhed blood aboundantly, and haſt made great wars, thou ſhalt not build an houſe to my name, becauſe thou haſt ſhed much blood upon the earth in my ſight.</hi> Is there no ſpirit and life in theſe words? Was not <hi>David</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to build the materiall Temple, a darke ſhadow and type of the ſpirituall? Was not he ſuffered in that age, under thoſe darke fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adminiſtrations, which held forth no greater light and put no greater glory upon their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to ſubdue the world, but by Sword and Bow, by force and violence: and is it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that the ſweet, mild and gentle ſpirit of the Goſpel, ſhould need the force and ſtrength of men <hi>Theſe doe well that it is in their hearts to reforme the world, but they miſtake the way;</hi> they act in the ſtrength of the wrath of God, in the ſpirit of this world; their poor earth will not conquer Hell and Devils, their Sword and Gunnes will never change the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of men: No, <hi>Solomon</hi> muſt build this Temple, the Lord Jeſus; it muſt bee another
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:44694:42"/>
ſpirit, another generation, another way: Theſe with <hi>David</hi> may fell the Cedars and hew the Stones of this earthly building. <hi>Thoſe ordain'd for this glorious worke, their Swords muſt bee of another mettall</hi> to wound and heale againe, to deſtroy the fleſh and transforme it into ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; their ſpirits ſhall breath forth nothing but love and ſweetneſſe; their Language ſhall be <hi>glory to God on high, on earth, peace, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will towards men;</hi> they call not for <hi>fire from Heaven,</hi> they caſt not into <hi>Priſons</hi> and <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons,</hi> they Plunder not nor deſtroy, they are of other ſpirits, more ſweet, more amiable, forcing the world by a divine power of love to confeſſe they are overcome and vanquiſh'd: All the Kingdomes of the Earth, all the Glory of the Creatures, all the Splendour, Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and Pompe of the world ſhall vaniſh as Smoake, and acknowledge it ſelfe a poore ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, an empty nothing. All that act in this ſpirit of violence and fury, are a rod in the hand of God, the Executioners of vengeance: <hi>Theſe are the Hornes of the Beaſts that ſhall hate the Whore, and make her deſolate, and naked, and ſhall eat her fleſh and burne her with fire, in the cup ſhee hath filled, theſe ſhall fill to her double; theſe powre out the Vials of wrath upon the ſeat of the Beaſts, they are the Fowles
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:44694:43"/>
of Heaven to eat the fleſh of Kings, and the fleſh of Captaines, and Great-ones of the earth; they are to rend and teare the outward gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the worlds glory; they are an admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration wherein God cloaths himſelf with fury &amp; indignation.</hi> By this ſpirit of vengeance and wrath, al the worlds torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tors have bin acted; this hath bin a work of <hi>Aſſir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ans</hi> and <hi>Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Romans, Turks</hi> and <hi>Sarazens;</hi> they have overco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the whole face of the earth with their Armies, they have trampled the Nations under their feet, and trod their God in the mire of the ſtreets. How doe many in this age, glory in theſe triumphs, ſet up their poor <hi>trophees,</hi> their triumphant Pillars, as if the ſtrength were their owne, and the glory their owne? Had they the <hi>ſpirits of Chriſtians, they needed not the ſwords of men; they are weake in the Spirit of the Goſpell, therefore they cloath themſelves with the power of fleſh,</hi> and will enter into <hi>Canaan</hi> in the wrath of the Lord, deſtroying and devouring, not converting: <hi>They glory in fleſhly Conqueſts and Victo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies,</hi> having not power in the <hi>Spirit</hi> to conquer in the way of <hi>love, union</hi> and <hi>peace:</hi> with theſe Weapons the Apoſtles bid defiance to the whole world, to Hell and Devils, they advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced their Standards upon the proud wals of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:44694:43"/>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe. This fleſhly ſtrength will prove weakneſſe in this worke; it will dye and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh into ayre, when it hath done the work the Lord hath appointed: God makes one ſpirit and property, of darkneſſe, afflict and torment another; the Nations of the world will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy themſelves, <hi>every one by the Sword of his Brother:</hi> The fleſh of the Saints engag'd in theſe conteſts and worldly quarrels, ſhall rend it ſelfe and helpe to rend the world: But how are they Saints? Such who have ſome glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merings of the <hi>bright and morning-Starre,</hi> who by throwing of the externall vaile of <hi>Antichriſtian darkneſſe, fleſhly forms ſervile dependency</hi> on the darke ſpirits of blind men; I ſay, having throwne of theſe fetters they have ſome liberty, and having remov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d theſe miſts they ſee a light, the faint reflections of a riſing Sunne, being let out of their cage of darkneſſe, they fly and flutter, and catch at eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, but apprehend little as it is in God; but in the light of their own ſpirits, mov'd by the call and drawing of the ſpirit of God, and the concurrence of thoſe <hi>beams of light</hi> ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered themſelves every where; theſe receive but glances and flaſhes, and cover it with much darkneſſe, confuſion and ignorance: yet being raiſ'd above their former ſtate they think God
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:44694:44"/>
ſpeaks in them, and their knowledge is the knowledge of the ſpirit. The good ſeem to <hi>give God the glory,</hi> and to make him their <hi>ſtrength in Battle;</hi> and conſidering how glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly they have conquered, are ſtrongly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that the mighty power of God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied them; and where God aſſiſts and gives victory, it muſt bee for good, for the good of mankinde and the world; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will improve their victories, to attain that high end. Thus they make their progreſſe; <hi>if God aſſiſts in acts of blood by force and figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, he doth the ſame in acts of force and violence upon the corrupt Governours of the World,</hi> who are running back into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> leaning upon the Pillars of the World; ſetting up their empty, <hi>guilded Idols,</hi> corrupt forms, and dark adminiſtrations, as the utmoſt end of all their endeavours, as the price of all the blood ſhed in the Kingdomes.</p>
               <p>Thus being perſwaded of the preſence of the Lord; and have in their own ſpirits ſome height and ſtrength to good, ſome will and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to doe good to the world, they continue their begun motion, meaſuring the whole by themſelves, the ſpirits of others by their own, and ſo think their whole body of aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, fitly qualified for the government of a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:44694:44"/>
Kingdome: Never conſidering what <hi>a ſpirit of darkneſſe, pride, vain-glory, Ambition,</hi> dwels and acts amongſt them, and how weak meer naturall ſpirits are, being <hi>raiſed from the duſt to ſit upon a throne,</hi> and to bear the temptations of Power, Honour, and worldly glory. Conſider actions purely and ſimply, according to their nature, and the diſpenſations of the Goſpel: This is a violent unnaturall fleſhly way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the reforming of the world; <hi>the ſmall ſtone muſt bee hewen out without hands.</hi> This is the winde rending and tearing the rocks, before the ſoft and ſtill voice was heard: This is the fire and Earth-quake to burn and ſhake this earthly fabrick, the corrupt world and its glory. Thus <hi>the Parliament have been executioners of vengeance upon the Kings party;</hi> who for judgement, a fire of wrath kindled in the bowels of the Kingdom, ſetting the properities of darkneſſe at enmity amongſt themſelves: <hi>A darke and formall Clergie, againſt a more dark and formall; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality</hi> and hypociſie againſt looſeneſſe and profaneſſe; reſtrained civilty againſt riot and luxury: The Miniſters preach war, and the ſword, and fire from heaven; diſcovering their own weakneſſe unable to act in the ſtrength of God; therefore they cry up the Cauſe of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:44694:45"/>
Religion, the Covenant, the Ordinances: theſe (though under more light then the other) yet they ſtir up the ſpirits of men, to afflict and torment their perſecutors, <hi>King, Prelats, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants,</hi> and to take away their revenues and honours. Far be it from me, to blaſt the leaſt appearance of God amongſt them, or to ſpread a cloud upon thoſe faint glimmerings which ſhin'd in their ſpirits: It was their darkneſſe, their fleſh, that made them thus <hi>excentrick;</hi> they acted in the ſpirit of the world, and of nature; their light was lightnings from Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> not the glorious light of the <hi>Spirit.</hi> In this way, they will be like the billowes and waves of the <hi>Sea,</hi> one toſſing and driving forward; the other, till they daſh themſelves againſt the rocks.</p>
               <p>The Parliament and their Armies have bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the <hi>Cavaliers;</hi> the <hi>Presbytery, Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> the <hi>Independents</hi> have reſtrained the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> for their pride and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes; giving them of the Cup, they gave others to drink. If the <hi>Independents</hi> corrupt, there are thoſe ſprung out of their own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels, prepared for their executioners: theſe, if they aſpire too high, will be <hi>Levell'd</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by their great Idoll the People; or their principles will raiſe a ſpirit dwelling in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:44694:45"/>
the confuſed rabble and multitude, to break and tear all to pieces, to bring all into a hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and confuſion, without order, law, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Thus the fury of the Lord breaks forth, like a burning fire, againſt all corruption in the powers of the world, againſt tyranny and oppreſſion in all its formes and ſhapes; though its Woolviſh ſpirit is cloathed with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency and gentleneſſe, the outward form will not change the nature; <hi>Monarchy, Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocracie, Democracie,</hi> will be much at one, unleſſe the breath of life from heaven quicken their dead &amp; liveleſs carkaſſes. I fear in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts we have too much mixed earth with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; we have gone a dark n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trodden obſcure path; <hi>therefore the Lord may juſtly withdraw that ſpirit of juſtice and righteouſnes; which hath accompanied and acted even more world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly States and Republikes.</hi> They acted in the fleſh; we pretend to a higher principle, we ſpeak of ſpirit, and power, and divine light; their motions were naturall according to their natures, being of the earth, earthly: ours ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular excentrick, unnaturall, being we think our ſelves heavenly, live in the aire of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, in the light of the Spirit; which points us out a more glorious way: therefore it is but juſt with God, if when we ſow the winde, we
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:44694:46"/>
reap the whirl-winde. But what will be the end of all? <hi>when wee have prov'd our own ſtrength to be weakneſſe; when our overturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall ſucceed another, that glorious power ſhall manifeſt it, whoſe right it is alone to reign: when we have paſſed through a wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the Lord will bring us into the Land of reſt,</hi> ſo long breathed after and deſired; <hi>the Lord will bring order out of confuſion, light out of darkneſſe, peace out of war and troubles:</hi> This will as ſurely be, as the ſpring now ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds the winter, the day the night: who the Lord may make moſt glorious, in this work, known alone to himſelfe: It magnifies his power and goodneſſe, if he breaths life in thoſe dead bones, which we trample upon: if he quickens thoſe which we have reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and rejected, as wither'd branches, and vile excrements. <hi>He can make the firſt laſt, and the laſt firſt;</hi> he can bring down the proud ſpirit of a <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> and force him to glorifie the God of Heaven. In the mean time, let every man keep his own ſtation; let the people of God ſhine like themſelves, that it may appear they are ſent into the world to do good to the world, &amp; to reflect the image and glory of God. Thoſe that are magiſtrates, let them put forth the ſpirits of Chriſtians, let
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:44694:46"/>
their actions bee convincing, let not the world juſtly brand them for corrupt, unjuſt, ſelf-advancers, and raiſers their families, rather then reſtorers of the ruines of a kingdome: if the floods of darkneſſe roars againſt them, and a deluge of confuſion overflows; if the flames of diviſion breake out again, let them be confident, they are above the danger in, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Region, where no cloud can reach them, no confuſion diſturb them: and if their earthlyes here, their bodies of duſt; yet they ſhall dwell ſecurely in theſe burnings, and be at peace in the middeſt of theſe flames. Thus Sir, I have given you my thoughts of the times; My earneſt deſire is, that things may prove otherwiſe then I write in relation to thoſe now in power; the Lord if it be his will make their actions glorious, and overule that ſpirit of perverſeneſſe and darknes, mingling it ſelf with their counſels: but if they faile, the Lord will doe the work; let us build upon this, as upon a rock, it is fixed and immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Sir, excuſe me, I have been too tedious, impute it to the ſubject I write, which affords matter for a volume; I have this confidence in you, that nothing will be unwelcome to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:44694:47"/>
you, from a friend, or a Chriſtian, or him who really is,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your kinſman and ſervant in every relation. H. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="letter">
               <head>Letter 11. An Anſwer of a Letter written by a friend.</head>
               <opener>
                  <date>June 8.</date>
                  <salute>Oh friend!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome two nights agoe, I ſaw a Bible, and found a deſire to look into it; but preſently my ſpirit checked me, ſaying, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me; <hi>What ſhouldeſt thou be peeping into that which thou canſt not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand? Stay till the light of the Lord ſhall lead thee, and then go whither it ſhall lead thee, till then every motion, and deſire cannot but be bitter, and the more it is hearkened unto, the more bitter:</hi> Yet my ſpirit ſaid again, within me; <hi>Why ſhould I refuſe this motion, though
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:44694:47"/>
griefe and bitterneſſe may attend it? may it not be good to ſee how dark and ignorant I am become?</hi> In the middeſt of ſuch reaſonings, I opened the Book; the firſt place I looked on, was very ſtrange to me; thence I turned from place to place, but thick darknes covered eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place; even thoſe which formerly ſeemed very clear to me. At laſt, I lighted on a place, which did ſomewhat affect me, then I took up the Book into a Chamber, thinking to ſuck a little ſweetnes, or at leaſt to vent a little of that load which had lain exceeding heavy on me all the day; ſo I read ſome ſix Chapters at leaſt, together (though with much adoe) they were the laſt Chapt. of <hi>Eſay:</hi> ſo ſoon as I had done, I fell into a very grievous paſſion, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold into what a ſtate I was caſt, for I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not one tittle, but confuſion and darknes covered and hid every thing from me: faine would I have faſtened on ſomewhat to have ſupported my ſpirit, to hope and wait for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes; but it would not bee: I could not conceive concerning whom thoſe things were ſpoken, or what that <hi>Zion</hi> is to whom they ſeem to be ſpoken. Indeed, I could not but weep outwardly, and mourn inwardly to think on my preſent darknes, which is ſo thick, that on
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:44694:48"/>
no manner of light comes in at any crevis. The Book of the creatures, the book of providence (as I was wont to call it) this book of the ſcriptures, which was once unutterably ſweet, and bright, and living; they are all become now dead, dark; but yet powerfull and peir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing tormentors.</p>
               <p>In the middeſt of theſe workings of minde, I fell (I know not how) to think of your let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and your deſire to hear from me, wondring at both; both, why you ſhould write ſo to me, and why you ſhould deſire to hear from me, as if either I could apprehend what you wrote, or tell how to ſpeak, or write any thing to you, in this ſtate of darknes, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular paſſages of your letter came into my minde, more increaſing this my amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The firſt clauſe of your letter did kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in me a great deſire to expoſtulate with you about it: I muſt break off, I can proceed no further now.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="letter">
               <head>Letter 12.</head>
               <opener>
                  <date>June 6.</date>
                  <salute>Oh friend!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I am heart-ſick, what ſhall I doe? I am ſick unto death, and yet am miſerable, becauſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:44694:48"/>
I cannot dye; I finde death as farre removed from me as life. I thought I had been dead and buried long agoe, and had nothing to do for the future, but to wait for a reſurrection from death, and out of the grave; but I feele my ſelf much alive to torment; and yet why may I not be dead for all that? ſpirituall death and a ſpirituall grave may have a kind of life in them, for ought I know. I cannot go on with the relation about thy letter; ſhall I try if I can open my breaſt, and give the a little glance of the miſery and oppreſſion that it lyes burde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with: I finde three tormentors within me, and they are continually ravening upon me, rending and tearing my head, my heart, my bowels. The names that I beſt know them by are <hi>Love, Griefe, fury:</hi> They commonly all ruſh forth upon me at once, though ſome one of them ſtill more predominantly then the reſt, feeding upon every object that is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to me, and heightning the diſeaſe and ſickneſſe of my ſpirit thereby.</p>
               <p>Sometimes Love tyrannizes, and makes me pant immeaſurably after ſome glimpſe of that my ſpirit is in love with; but what it is, or where it is, I know not; when I hear the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:44694:49"/>
birds, or ſee any other creature in the <hi>heavens above, or in the earth beneath:</hi> Oh think I, that I were behind thee, that I might diſcern thy ſubſtance, and ſee whether that be my love or no: When I ſee their tendernes towards their young ones, the employment they are buſied with, the delight they can ſuck in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>: Oh where am I, what am I, how farr laid below the whole creation? who finde no employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no delight, none to look after me, no bowels to anſwer the ſounding of my bowels. Some what I love, but I know not what, nor where to ſeek after, nor what name to enquire for it by. Shall I go to the woods, among the wilde Hindes? Alas, they are as unable to heare, as I am to ſpeak: ſhall I ask the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort of men? They, poore creatures ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver think of any ſuch thing. Shall I ask Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? Ah! they as inſenſible of my condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as any of the reſt; and all the news I can heare of them is of <hi>melancholy,</hi> and giving way to temptation, and wiſh me to uſe the means which is as impoſſible to me; as to finde out my love without them: <hi>Oh miſerie, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie!</hi> to love one knows not what, or where; to have love kindled, and the beloved quite loſt; to have love flaming, and nothing for its
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:44694:49"/>
flames to go forth upon, but ſtill to feed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in upon the boſome wherein it breeds: I finde this ſometimes make theſe earthly bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels ſo yearn, as if they would immediately melt and drop out of the body; wherein they are as yet contained.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Love</hi> hath wearied it ſelf, then <hi>Grief</hi> (though it was not abſent before) ſupplies its place, in panting, in ſighing, in mourning, in complaining, if it can: <hi>Oh God! oh my God! oh living God! oh my beloved!</hi> (theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions it uſes for forms ſake, though it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands them not) <hi>What are thou? Where art thou? Verily, thou art a God that hideſt thy ſelf; what no news of thec? Why doſt thou open my bowels, when thou meaneſt to ſhut up thine own? What is become of thee? Haſt not thou a diſcovering art, as well as an hiding art? When wilt thou open thy ſelf? I cannot finde thee out, I cannot viſit thee; wilt thou never beſtow a viſit on me, ſhall I never be remembred? Shall I never know what God means more? A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſt I alwayes be tormented among ſhadows, longing and wand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring after the ſubſtance, and never meet with it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All this while it is pretty well, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:44694:50"/>
of what it is, when fury <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> my ſpirit boils within me, and rages;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is that maketh my ſpirit ſo violent and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ous, I can in no wiſe imagine, nor vent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cannot, it is too big to come forth: ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no object without capacious enough to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceive it; but within it lyes, and feeds, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> preſſes ſo vehemently, that my ſpirit is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> forced to cry out day and night; there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſubſiſting, no, there is no ſubſiſting und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <opener>
                     <date>June 10.</date>
                  </opener>
                  <p>NOw to return, if it may be to the thoughts and workings of my minde concerning your letter. To what end ſhould he write to me in this manner, unleſs he could withall have ſent me light to read by? <hi>I</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not one line, not one tittle of all his letter. <hi>This day whileſt my father and I was together this letter became yours:</hi> What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the meaning of this? which way ſhall <hi>I</hi> go <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> bout to finde out the meaning of this: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> he preſent, how many queſtions might <hi>I</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> him before <hi>I</hi> could receive in any imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:44694:50"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> concerning the ſenſe of theſe words? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>I</hi> muſt ask him, who is his father, what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> father? <hi>I</hi> cannot ſo much as fancy what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhould be: A father is he that begets, his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is he that begat him. But who is that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> begat him, what is he? <hi>I</hi> am at a loſſe at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> daſh. But what meanes this, <hi>Whileſt my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> and I was together,</hi> what is it to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the father, to have the father with one? here is a puzling phraſe indeed; here my fancy is quite puzled, I know not how to frame any imagination about this; what it is to be with the father. And <hi>whileſt I was with the father,</hi> what is the meaning of this <hi>whileſt,</hi> is hee ſometimes with the <hi>father,</hi> and ſometimes not with the <hi>father? Whileſt,</hi> I know not what to make of this whileſt: <hi>Whileſt I was with the father, this letter became yours?</hi> how mine? <hi>I</hi> know not how it is mine: how be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came it mine? Did his father, while he was with him bid him write this to me? Here may be more in this then I am aware of.</p>
                  <p>I remember my mind did much muſe on this, and my deſire was great to have ſatisfied my ſpirit concerning the ſence of it, but it was and ſtill is too hard for mee.</p>
                  <p>Then I thought on the next paſſage, <hi>That there is but one to remain on the earth, &amp; that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:44694:51"/>
is the Lord.</hi> But one, What is one? For my pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> I know neither unity nor diſtinction, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is the Lord. The Lord, Oh what is the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> who is the Lord? I am forced to ſpeake lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Pharaoh, I know not the Lord.</hi> I cannot ſay know any thing, nay certainly (if any thing b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> certaine to mee) I doe not know any thing But of all things I have no knowledge at all o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Lord, that is the thing indeed that is hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> from mee with perfect darkneſſe. The vaile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo thicke and my eye ſo weake (if I have an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eye) that I have no manner of diſcerning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> him. <hi>But one to remaine on the earth,</hi> Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> is this remaining? when all things paſſe awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall the earth it ſelfe abide any otherwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> then other things abide alſo? how ſhall th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Lord remaine on the earth?</p>
                  <p>Then I thought on that paſſage, <hi>Be not tro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</hi> What voyce is this? whence came this Did his father bid him w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ite thus to mee Who is it troubles me? To this let me ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> two things. I cannot reſiſt, alas what a vai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thing is it for a poore weake creature to thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to withſtand ſuch mighty powerfull troubl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as comes ruſhing in upon mee: I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtrength to reſiſt any thing, there is nothi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſo weake as I, the ſtrongeſt Engine is wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in my hand; but trouble hath growne
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:44694:51"/>
ſtrength as faſt as I have decayed, How ſhould I now reſiſt it? how ſhould I now avoid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng troubled: Beſides, when at at any time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thinke to keepe trouble of, it preſently o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-beares me, I never finde any mitigation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rouble (ſo farre as I have obſerved) but when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lye downe at its feet, opening my boſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd letting it enter as deepe as it will: What means this phraſe, whence came this ſpeech, <hi>Be not troubled?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then that paſſage came into my minde, <hi>If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ou will but ſtand ſtill you ſhall ſee the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ion of the Lord, breaking forth upon the whole earth.</hi> I did not finde my ſpirit ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring into the particular ſence of this Phraſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s working thus. How ſpake hee this? Upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> generall notion that the Lord will appeare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re long, and ſo I among others ſhall ſee him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ea perhaps he may meane though the body be laid in the duſt firſt, yet I ſhall ſee him: or by a particular preſent light from the father concerning me, whom he ſaid was now with him, and that while he was with him, this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er became mine.</p>
                  <p>Afterwards I remembred another paſſage, <hi>Shall I come to you, or will you come to mee?</hi> What was his intent in this, that the body <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hould move to him to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> or ſend to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:44694:52"/>
him to move to the place where my body then was? Alas, that were a poore comming on either hand, or to what end were any ſuch comming? and for any other comming ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mee to any, or of any to mee, I am not acquainted with it.</p>
                  <p>At laſt I remembred that, <hi>When he appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto mee my fleſh died and was crucified.</hi> Oh then I felt my ſpirit burne within mee to know this appearing of him, and the rather that it might kill me, that I might once ente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> into this crucified ſtate, oh this is a ſweet way of dying, to dye by the appearing of the Lord this is the very way I have deſired to dye al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this while. My torments have been partly welcome through hope of death from them and I reaſoned within my ſelfe, though th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lord might ſlay me by his appearing, yet if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> were his pleaſure to kill me by his abſence an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſeverall kindes of tormenting fires which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhould pick out to that purpoſe, yet at leng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> death would bee ſweet, and an entrance int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> my deſired life. But this was it ſtill perplex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> me, I could not dye, the flames wereliving fed mee with life, as well as with tormen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Then my Spirit would Sigh, <hi>Surely this wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> never do it, after this rate, may I be torment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> for ever, and yet ſtill live unto that, to whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="79" facs="tcp:44694:52"/>
I have ſtill deſired to dye.</hi> But to be killed by the appearing of the Lord, oh how ſweet would this way be! and this would be a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine way too, mee thinkes I could eaſily bee perſwaded to beleeve, that the creature can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live any longer when God once ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares.</p>
                  <p>To theſe let me add one more, which came into my minde this morning. <hi>Come let us be gone, why ſtay we here? our bed is greene.</hi> Oh how faine would I be gone! How doe I loath ſtaying here? I am manacled, I am ſhack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, I am faſtened with that which I loath, as well as with-held from that which I love, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen me and I will bee gone: yet ſtay, I muſt bee furniſhed with wings too, or I cannot mount up; my wings are clipped, I cannot fly with them: Oh that I had the wings of thy <hi>Dov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> then would I fly and bee at reſt! Why ſtay I here? but becauſe I am a Captive, held under miſery in my enemies land, by force and power, and there is none to reſcue, I am uſed moſt barbarouſly, ſtarved for want of food, ſtripped not only of my ornaments, but of my very cloathes, thruſt our of doores to lodge in what bed I can finde; and I looked for one to pitty, for one to redeeme and bring me back againeto my owne country, among
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:44694:53"/>
my owne freinds, to the free enjoyment of my owne inheritance, but woe is mee, ſtill the teares of the oppreſſed abound, but there is no Comforter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Our bed is greene.</hi> Oh ſure me thinkes I can imagine that to be ſweet. <hi>But my bed is black, a mourning bed, a bed of great tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a bed of widdowhood, a bed of ſorrowes and death, full of trouble, torment and teares in the night, a bed not fit to entertaine my bedfellow in, a bed I can neuer expect any reſt in. Oh a bed of reſt, a bed of injoyment, a bed made freſh and greene by the preſence of my Spouſe,</hi> when ſhall my wearied ſpirit know where ſuch a <hi>bed</hi> is, that it may have recourſe to it for ſome refreſhments?</p>
                  <p>My friend, theſe (except the laſt) were the confuſed and unexpected workings of my mind upon your Letter, which before I had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to thinke of, or meddle with, otherwiſe then <hi>I</hi> doe with all things, in an overly ſlight manner, with neither deſire towards them, nor expectation from them. But then my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire was ſomewhat quicker, either to have had you preſent, or to write thoſe things unto you while they were freſh in my thoughts, or to deſire your comming down hither, to ſee what
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:44694:53"/>
ſatisfaction you could give to ſuch demands as your ſelfe had occaſioned.</p>
                  <p>But ſudainly were all theſe ſilenced and put out, To what end are theſe? what if he were here? what if I might aske him all that is at preſent in my heart? What can he ſay to me? How can I heare him? Is not this the old ginne to entice thee to looke after the creature for ſomewhat, though not for that thou mainly deſireſt? This is a new device to lead thee ſtill to be acting and moving without the light of the Lord. It will bee better and more eaſie to be quiet, when wilt thou ceaſe from theſe kinde of motions and wait entirely for him who alone can ſatisfie thy <hi>reſtleſſe ſpirit?</hi> After a while I found my deſire quite fall flat, and theſe things to vaniſh out of my minde, I never intending more to looke backe upon them. But that day forementioned, in the afternoone, my torment increaſing upon mee, and theſe things comming againe into my minde, and withall a preſſing in me to write them, though my ſpirit diſrelliſhed the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet at length it aſſented, and went on then ſo farre as it could, and ſince as it found it ſelfe free, which way of acting by a preſent free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, though it declined, looking upon it as baſe and ſervile, yea a pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce of bondage, yet
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:44694:54"/>
it is at preſent forced backe againe unto it.</p>
                  <p>Thus at length you have a Letter, together with the occaſion of it, which I leave with you, and you to your reſt, and for my ſelfe, would returne if I could with freedome and delight, to the embracing of my ſtate of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry &amp; every particular pang of miſerie therein: And would ſubſcribe my ſelf if I knew what I were, either in my ſelfe or in relation to thee. Or at leaſt I would bid thee farewell, if I could but ſpeake it underſtandingly: But thou canſt doe it without my bidding thee. Doe that and onely that which thou art led to by infallible light and pure power, and then thou treadeſt in the ſteps in which I long to follow thee. But away with fancies, conceits and imaginations, though faſtened upon the word, or fancied to bee flowing from the Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Truth, Truth, Truth, true Life, true Light, true Power, not a connterfeit Image, but the thing it ſelfe,</hi> Oh where is it <hi>Walford?</hi> Doe not deceive me, but tell me whether thou haſt it or no? How joyfull would it be to mee were I ſatisfied that it were upon the march, and had already taken poſſeſſion of ſome of my fellow Priſoners! But how fooliſh and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:44694:54"/>
vaine am I! Sure it is time to breake off.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <opener>
                     <date>June 11.</date>
                  </opener>
                  <p>NOW my preſent ſtate contradicts this, for my pangs of griefe are ſo extreame, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y ſeeme to exceed my pangs of fury, and my ſpirit as reſtleſſe under them, as it can be under the other, My ſpirit would faine ſay, <hi>O awake not my love till he pleaſe,</hi> but the ſharpneſſe of greife will not ſuffer. Then my Spirit burſt forth into reaſonings, <hi>This is but thy will to have thy beloved preſent, tis his will to bee abſent, thou ſaiſt thou wouldſt have thy will fall and his onely ſtand, Can this bee ſo and yet thou ſo vehemently greive becauſe thy will is croſſed and his ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled?</hi> Then greife gives my <hi>ſpirit</hi> ſuch a nip that it is glad to bee rid of ſuch thoughts. At laſt ſaid my Spirit within me, <hi>lye downe under this greife, paſſe through greife as well as fury, let it worke, let it rend, let it teare.</hi> This is like an heape of ſtubble, turnes griefe into ſuch a flame that it torments more; that the poore
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:44694:55"/>
wretch cannot poſſibly lyeſtill, or ſtirre, but ſtil whenſoever it does, is worſt</p>
                  <p>Mee thinkes I cannot but take notice what a grievous Lyarſence is, it will ſtill be judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and yet is unable to judge concerning the things of ſence, but now ſaies this is bitter, and by and by contradicts it ſelfe. Now I am wiſe and can obſerve the folly of ſence, I looke to be met with for this.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="letter">
               <head>12. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Can cheerefully ſerve pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in writing to you, though I had rather doe it in ſilence, for I know that God does moſt when man does leaſt. Yet ſince God is pleaſed in ſome meaſure to come in with them, and the Spirit is drawn out to deſire them, I am the more willing to correſpond with you in this kind, you doe well in eying God more then me in them, yet God
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:44694:55"/>
will bee moſt glorious, when his <hi>diſpenſations</hi> will bee ſo naked, as wee can eye him in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but himſelfe. God will ere long let us ſee that meanes are but vailes, though in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with our weakneſſe hee hath made uſe of them; while he appeared by candle-light, and in darker diſcoveries hee made uſe of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks, he gave as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Epheſ. 4. Some Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Evangeliſts, ſome Paſtors and Teachers, till we all come in the unity of the faith and the knowledge of the Sonne of God to a perfect man,</hi> &amp;c. And when that which is perfect is come, that which is in part ſhall bee done away. God hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto (as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did by his brethren) ſpoken to us by an interpreter, becauſe hee would act at more diſtance, but when grace and love can contain no longer, God will (as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did) command all <hi>to goe forth,</hi> and cry out <hi>I am hee,</hi> and ſhow himſelfe in uncovered clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; this adminiſtration God hath entred upon already in ſome of his people, and they beginne to get a glimpſe of the face of God, and are acquainted with immediate actings in their owne hearts. I thinke the laſt meanes that God will make uſe of, will be ſuch as the creature will be glad to be free from, I meane perſecution, reproach, poverty, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:44694:56"/>
ſomewhat more terrible and contrary to wiſe and proud fleſh, then all this; for as for theſe means of preaching, praying, gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, wherein the <hi>creature</hi> can be active and hououred, and ſerve God and it ſelfe, and goe halfe with him (as I may ſay) in point of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the creature will with a great deale of reluctancy bee drawne from them, for truly there's much credit comes into us by ſuch things, and uſually thoſe who openly hate us, doe inwardly honour us for them, beſides the ſecret confidence and comfort that our ſelves and friends have in them: But when God ſhall adminiſter under ſuch meanes as we ſhall be more paſſive in, and ſuch as will ſift us to the very <hi>ſoule</hi> and <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and let us know all that is in our <hi>hearts,</hi> ſuch as will cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to be ſuſpected of our ſelves, ſleighted by others, forſaken of our freinds, and ſuch too as have not onely beene one fleſh, but one ſpirit with us; when <hi>religion</hi> ſhall come to that paſſe, that he that will profeſſe Chriſt, muſt profeſſe poverty, diſgrace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then we ſhall be glad to be freed from the meanes, and to have God be all in all, for in this way that <hi>Saints</hi> are in for preſent, they are ſo rich and abounding, as I doe not wonder, they are offended that God will ſtrip the <hi>creature</hi> naked, and bee all
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:44694:56"/>
himſelfe. Verily its a terrible thing for one that hath thriven in the things of God, and grown rich in reputation, to be adminiſtred in ſuch a way as <hi>Profeſſors</hi> themſelves will thinke him an <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> and thoſe that are more charitable, a deluded or a mad man; well, God in himſelf will make amends for God in the ſevereſt <hi>diſpenſations.</hi> And there is that man-child ere long to be brought forth in us in ſpirit and truth; (which wee have hitherto been delivered of in fleſh and darke appearances) and when he comes, <hi>the wilderneſſe and ſolitary place ſhall be glad for him,</hi> or as <hi>Eſay</hi> in another place, <hi>Wee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to</hi> Sion <hi>with Songs and everlaſting joy upon our heads,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> carries it further yet, 1 <hi>John 3. 2. When hee ſhall appeare wee ſhall be like him, for wee ſhall know him as hee is.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your loving</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="letter">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:44694:57"/>
               <head>13. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Lately received three Letters from you and ſome Books for which I thank you: As for Mr. <hi>Sedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicks</hi> book I am not to tell you at preſent what I think of it; God will doe great things by himſelf: the Army and all that they ſettle, muſt be deſtroyed without hands; the Spirit will blow upon <hi>all fleſh,</hi> and yet they are to ſettle, becauſe drawn out ſo to do; and their ſetting up is Gods work, as well as his throwing down; he doth the one by the creature, the other by himſelf. I think the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of the Army are in their kinde ſo righteous, as man will not be able to diſſolve them; but becauſe <hi>all fleſh is gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe,</hi> it muſt wither, God will be great to the ends of the earth, and every thing ſhall be reſtored into the glorious liberty <hi>of the Sons of God; the heavens ſhall no longer con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> him: The earth ſhall be fild with knowledge of God: the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:44694:57"/>
earth ſhall bee ſanctified by the Word, by the manifeſtation of God upon it;</hi> things ſhall not be morally but ſpiritually reſtored; the Serpent ſhall be ſhut out of Paradiſe; the Tree of Life ſhall grow on both ſides the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: Publicans and Sinners ſhall rejoyce, the wiſe and prudent ſhall mourn, all the beaſts of the field ſhall rejoyce and feed on the Tree of Life; the Serpent ſhall be glutted with duſt, judgement ſhall dwell in the wilderneſſe; the high-way ſhall be holineſſe; there ſhall bee no more ſin, for there ſhall bee no more ſelf, and no more curſe, <hi>but the fruit of the earth ſhall be beautifull and comely, for death and hell ſhall be caſt into the lake of fire: Thou art righteous oh Lord which art, which waſt, and ſhall bee, becauſe thou haſt judged thus: Let the heavens be glad and the earth rejoyce; Let the Sea roare, and the fulnes thereof; for he commeth, for he commeth to judge the earth, he ſhall judge the world with righteouſnes, and the people with truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours in the Lord.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="letter">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:44694:58"/>
               <head>14. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OURS came to my hands, when your friends were with mee, who all of them in much free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome injoy your bondage, <hi>till he that hath the Keyes of the bottomleſſe Pit ſhall releaſe you.</hi> Its good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Hell ſometimes for variety, and to be in the Sea, to ſee the wonders of God in the deep, <hi>I</hi> have beene lately my ſelfe in the bottome of it, where <hi>I</hi> found a <hi>Pearle,</hi> that's richer then the earth, and <hi>I</hi> doubt not but provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence will prepare you a table in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe too. It hath been the Lot of all of us to be where you are, and <hi>I</hi> thinke ſome of us ſtay behinde on purpoſe to beare you company. <hi>The bright day muſt bee brought in by the darkeſt night, and the voyce at midnight will be, the Bridegroome is come.</hi> Since the fleſh muſt dye, it were well it were killed at once, yet ſince the execution is ſo terrible, its mercy we dye by degrees, dye daily, and if we did not
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:44694:58"/>
dye too, ſo as to perceive that we dye, it would doe us no good; however it is beſt you ſhould be diſpenſed as you are, becauſe God will have it as it is, <hi>whoſe will is the rule of goodneſſe,</hi> and not our underſtanding.</p>
               <p>I conceive the reaſon why you have not heard from thoſe your friends all this time, is, becauſe they were not at home; they were abſent from the Lord, ſure it will not be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes thus; but ſo long as there is any thing of earth in us, there will bee <hi>Eclipſes</hi> and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: when wee are caught up into the ayre we ſhall be ever with the Lord.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours in the Lord.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="letter">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:44694:59"/>
               <head>15. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Loving Siſter,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Love remembred to you, and to the reſt of my Siſters, hoping that you are in good health, as I am at this preſent; Theſe lines are for to certifie you concerning the preſent dealings of God with me: He hath been pleaſed to make known much of himſelf, and doth make me claim my ownes with himſelf, ſaying; <hi>That all things are of himſelf, and that he hath made out himſelf into ſo many beeings as there are viſible creatures; and that God is compleat in all things unto viſible apprehenſion;</hi> but it is the great wiſdome of God, for to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat himſelf in that being, that the wiſdome of the world cannot comprehend him, for God now is accompliſhing that great myſtery which he hath ſpoken off in the Letter; <hi>I will work a worke in your dayes, that yee would not believe, although it be told unto you; for this is that great myſtery of God which he is now accompliſhing;</hi> that none but himſelf, can
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:44694:59"/>
know himſelf in his being; and this is the dealings of God, to beget of himſelf, and when he hath begotten at the fulneſſe of time, he doth bring forth, and when he hath brought forth then doth he make known himſelf, to himſelf; for there is none but himſelf, doth know him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his beeing: <hi>I</hi> have much more to ſay, but not being acquainted with your Spirit at preſent, I ſhall let it reſt; leaving you unto him, who doth order all things of himſelf: I am for the preſent a priſoner, in the accompt of reaſon, yet at libertie; and did never enjoy more of the fulneſſe of God, then <hi>I</hi> have ſince I came into that place; for I ſee that it is not priſon doores, that will keep God out from himſelf; but he will ſhine in with ſo much glory, as will cauſe ſo much excellency to the apprehenſion of a creature, that will make him to ſay, <hi>I am not onely willing to be bound, but to die in the enjoyment of my God;</hi> Thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring you to remember mee to my loving friends, <hi>I reſt</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Brother</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="letter">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:44694:60"/>
               <head>Letter 16.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T preſent, I have no free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to anſwer the Letter, but am glad to hear from you: the main ground of my ſhattering, lyes here: I am diſappointed of that which I had as certain an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of in my ſpirit, as any thing that ever paſſed through me at any time, which ſits ſo neere me, as I think, it will haſten my death; it was the onely thing in the world my heart was ſet on; and I uſed to ſay, there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing betwixt God and me, but it; in that, I am happy, and at a great deal of eaſe, that <hi>I</hi> have loſt every thing that my heart was inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate on, but the diſappointment of that which came with ſo much certainty into my ſoule, is the onely thing that ſo much unſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles me. <hi>I</hi> have no thoughts of going in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate or more plauſible way to heaven; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was <hi>I</hi> over much under that temptation.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:44694:60"/>
                  <hi>I</hi> have no thoughts of carrying my reputation whol to heaven; 'tis too much torn already, &amp; <hi>I</hi> am glad it is ſo. <hi>I</hi> think no temptation but one of this nature <hi>I</hi> mention, could poſſibly ſhake me as it doth: what you ſay, <hi>concerning the burning of the droſſe, that did accompany theſe actings, I</hi> cloſe with, and haply there's no more in it: <hi>I like well your living in the light, and will of God; its a ſweet beeing, and which for the preſent, I am debarred of: I</hi> pray you let me hear as aft as you can; <hi>I</hi> love your letters, not onely for your ſake, but their own; beſides it will ſomewhat diminiſh my ſolitude. <hi>I</hi> have no freedome to go to,—though oft ſent for; but to ſit ſtill and enjoy my own unquietnes,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>I am yours,</signed>
Farewell.</closer>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="letter">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:44694:61"/>
               <head>Letter 17.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Uſe not after a free propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of truth, to proſecute it in a carnall way, either by anſwering the argument of others, or enforcing it with my own; truth will doe better without our tampering with it; and we cannot force our paſſage to ſpiritual things by dint of diſcourſe; but muſt wait for pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from on high: where as you are ſcrupled, that Chriſt was not often mentioned in my letter; you know there may bee much of Chriſt in effect, where there is but little in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance; and that hath bin the great unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the world, that we have had ſo much of Chriſt in ſound, and ſo little in ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>For your jealouſie; <hi>that what I ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the departure of Heaven and earth, might be a deluſion: I</hi> refer you to that proof in <hi>Eſay</hi> that accompanied it; and if you think the ſcripture to be rather pretended, then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:44694:61"/>
made uſe of, in favour of what was writ: <hi>I</hi> confeſſe <hi>I</hi> give ſo much to the dictates of God in my heart, as to entertain them upon their own authority, and know God ſo well, as <hi>I</hi> dare take his word without his hand: Neither doe <hi>I</hi> think that onely to be the word of God which is written; the Apoſtle ſeems to extend it further, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 17. where, the article (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) in the originall refers to ſpirit, as if he had ſaid, which ſpirit is the word of God. See <hi>Jo.</hi> 6. 63. it is onely the word that is <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> that can doe us good; for the letter of the word, can onely produce a literal evidence, and for that purpoſe <hi>I</hi> cited ſcripture in a condeſcenſion to your weaknes, til God would be pleaſed to ſet it on with the inward as well as the outward word: whereas you think <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> will be exceedingly advantaged by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall of ſcripture, I think ſo too; <hi>but it will be by a denyall of the Spirit, and not the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall ſcripture; for we know 'tis the bright appearances of Spirit in the Saints, that will make an end of him:</hi> And in relation to this brightnes of the comming of Chriſt, and this day ſtar ariſing in the heart; the ſcripture is cal'd, <hi>a light ſhining in a dark place:</hi> and ſoken of there as a letter light, that muſt give place to a greater: 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19. For your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:44694:62"/>
of waiting upon God in that light you have, you doe well; he that believeth makes not haſt, and (as you ſay) its viſion that muſt convince you, and nothing elſe: <hi>Be of good comfort,</hi> the viſion is for an appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time, <hi>but at the end it ſhall ſpeak and not lye; though it tarry wait for it, becauſe it will ſurely come, it will not tarry,</hi> Hab. 2. 3.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your loving friend, &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="letter">
               <head>18. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> DOE a little depart from my ſelfe, in the indeavouring the ſatisfaction in ſuch a carnall way as this; my writing will not doe that in a long time which your waiting may doe ſhortly; that which muſt doe you good is not diſcourſe but viſion, and that is for an appointed time; <hi>our ſeaſons of refreſhing are in the hand of God, and ſilence is the earneſt of comfort, and the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:44694:62"/>
ſatisfaction is then neereſt, when you are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent it ſhould be as farre of as God would have it.</hi> For your deſire of being with mee, <hi>I</hi> looke on it not onely as a ſignification of the <hi>love,</hi> but as a ſmoaking of the <hi>flax</hi> which will blaze ere long notwithſtanding all that water which <hi>I</hi> perceive hath beene caſt upon it. For the jealouſie of your friends in returning to me, ſo farre as it may relate to your preſent exerciſe, <hi>I</hi> am well content you ſhould be where you are, if that work be of God, which (<hi>I</hi> hope) is begunne in you, they cannot fruſtrate it, and if it be not, <hi>I</hi> cannot further it; beſides <hi>I</hi> rather deſire you ſhould be ſet in ſuch circumſtances as the worke of God in you may have leſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on man and more upon God; and if in the midſt of all oppoſitions, truth ſhall make good its being in you, you muſt then needes cry out, that this was the finger of God. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that which ſcruples you about Chriſt and the Scriptures, <hi>I</hi> ſhall only ſay this, if God will take them away in fleſh and reſtore them in Spirit, we have not loſt but improved them, we have hitherto had a very low and fleſhly uſe of both. Your temptation herein ſeemes to be the ſame with the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> who in that low and literall adminiſtration, could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to heare of <hi>Chriſts</hi> departure, when as
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:44694:63"/>
by that meanes his preſence was improved, they who had him with them before, had him in them afterward, as we have had likewiſe in our meaſure, in a <hi>diſpenſation</hi> of <hi>gifts</hi> and <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> out of which if <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall withdraw, and returne in a more immediate and naked adminiſtration of himſelfe upon us, as (<hi>I</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve) hee is now beginning in the ſpirits of many of his people; we have more of <hi>Chriſt</hi> then ever. <hi>I</hi> could draw out this at large, in reference to your preſent ſcruple, but the <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier</hi> haſtens me, and <hi>I</hi> can but ſatisfie the fleſh or reaſon, its the inward annointing that muſt ſatisfie the Spirit, and lead you into all truth.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your loving Freind,</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="letter">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:44694:63"/>
               <head>19. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Deare Soule</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Received thy Letter, and am very ſenſible of thy condition being called of God every moment in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his <hi>worke-houſe,</hi> where I met with ſuch imployment, as hath drunke the well of peace and joy for ever, and I have no hope ever to ſee thoſe ſtreames flow again but would be glad <hi>to be in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe pit for ever.</hi> If Gods preſence did not alwayes kindle ſuch a fire, before which I cannot ſtand; and I muſt ſay, <hi>Who can ſtand when he appeares to famiſh all the Gods of the earth, and to hide himſelfe from himſelfe, which condition makes mee reell to and frow like a drunken man, and oft cry out in the bitterneſſe of ſpirit, I would I had never beene borne,</hi> but whileſt I am pouring of my complaints into thy boſome, a noyſe of peace beganne to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare and ſayd, <hi>affliction is the Saints for a moment, but the worlds for ever; the Saints to refine them, but the worlds conſume them for
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:44694:64"/>
ever: O how could I mourne over the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like men and women of the world, for who is ſo God-like as they that can tell what a crucified Chriſt is in their owne ſpirits that can ſhew his wounds, and ſay, he is dead in me,</hi> which the world cannot I am ſure: but I ſhall not long mourne for them, and for oft I know the laſt groane is gone forth of my breaſt that ever I muſt groane for them; but <hi>I</hi> muſt goe forth in judgement with my Father, and praiſe him for the victory which hee will have over them.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Son farewell, for a little ſeaſon, while our all will bring us together againe in himſelfe and place us in the ſtill fountaine of peace and, joy for ever.
<hi>Farewell.</hi>
                  </salute>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="letter">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:44694:64"/>
               <head>20. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Muſt needs write, though haply 'twere better for you I did not, <hi>I</hi> am ſenſible of your condition and cannot but in this fleſhly way of counſell and comfort corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond with you, when as if my mouth were ſhut, God would open his, and ſpeake that peace in a moment, which <hi>I</hi> know better how to darken then declare, for <hi>I</hi> am clearer in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing then this, that our tampering with the meanes doth vaile God, though <hi>I</hi> confeſſe while <hi>Saints</hi> were under an inferior admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration: our uſe of meanes might be of ſome ſervice to us. <hi>I</hi> ſee now God in his moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious flowings upon our hearts, either uſes no meanes, or ſuch as proud fleſh would thinke fitter, to hinder then promote ſuch an end; you little thinke that the perſecution (for 'tis no other) that you have undergone of late, hath done you much more ſervice, then either
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:44694:65"/>
my preſence or Letters, and it were beſt for you that perſecution had had its perfect work and that <hi>I</hi> had ſtood ſtill, and not ſeconded you at all: <hi>I</hi> knew well, that when you were at the loweſt ebb, and confeſſing the worke of God in you, to be nothing but a deluſion, that you were then travelling with a more excellent diſcovery, which would ariſe with ſo much glory and evidence upon your Spirit, as it would ſwallow up all oppoſition, and turn into ſuch a diſappointment of fleſh &amp; blood, as would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>found all that ſought to captivate the appearances of God in you, and to glory in the fleſh: How unanſwerable are the diſcoveries of God in you, which when both your freinds and ſelfe had diſowned, you ſhould yet vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their owne being, in the ſoule. For your deſire of comming to me, if it proceed from a wearineſſe of your condition at <hi>Norwich,</hi> or a carnall confidence in my preſence, you will certainly bee fruſtrated in the end, you are beſt where God hath ſet you, Read <hi>Eſay</hi> 28. 16. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 9, 10. and let me add with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, if you deſire to runne that courſe that <hi>I</hi> thinke providence will direct me in, you muſt reſolve upon reproach, poverty, perſecution, what not, for <hi>I</hi> am perſwaded that <hi>I</hi> ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe all this, therefore be well adviſed and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:44694:65"/>
conſider before hand what a compliance with me will coſt. Truly whiles <hi>Saints</hi> were in a mixt condition, though the world hated the Spirit in them, yet they could cloſe with what was fleſh, and both met in that <hi>medium:</hi> But when fleſh ſhall bee wholly ſwallowed up in Spirit the whole world almoſt will hate us, there being nothing left that their approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will take hold of; when there ſhall bee nothing but God within, there will bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but enmity without: 'Tis enough that the love of God will make amends for the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of all the world; and the leſſe we have of God in the creature, the more we have of God in himſelfe. Thoſe times make haſte upon the world, wherein that terrible <hi>Propheſie</hi> in the 21. of <hi>Luke</hi> will bee fulfilled, though <hi>I</hi> conceive it will bee in ſpirit and not in fleſh, and ſuch a way as our reaſon hath imagined. <hi>I</hi> am aſtoniſhed at the glory that will bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the <hi>Saints,</hi> when God hath ſo ſhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered us out of all inferior actings, as the world will count us <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the world, but even the <hi>Saints</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo farre as they judge according to the outward appearance; the <hi>Sonne</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe muſt deliver up the Kingdome to his <hi>Father,</hi> which is an adminiſtration of <hi>gifts</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:44694:66"/>
and <hi>graces,</hi> before God can bee all in all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bee of good comfort, there is that myſtery of godlineſſe and glory to bee manifeſted in us, with which all the ſufferings of this life, and whatever elſe can betide us in our way to it, are not worthy to bee compared;</hi> in the very expectation whereof <hi>I</hi> am ſeiſed with more joy then my poore heart can hold.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours in all conditions.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="letter">
               <head>Letter 21.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Purpoſed the laſt week to have ſaluted my friends, and ſee now the reaſon why providence diſappointed me, which I ſhall keep ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret to my ſelf. For your Letter I ſhould have been troubled at it, had not <hi>I</hi> learned to ſee God in every thing, and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:44694:66"/>
been acquainted with thoſe traverſes of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reaſon and unbelief in my own Spirit; you have done no more then what <hi>I</hi> have done my ſelf, concluding both with my ſelf, and in the company of my friends, the ſame things to be no better then deluſions, and under that temptation of blaſphemy againſt the Spirit, have reſted till a brighter appearance of God hath broke through all, and ſwallowed up that veile of death and darknes in ſo much victory; as <hi>I</hi> muſt needs confeſſe my ſelf to have been more then a conquerer, though it hath coſt me dear firſt. For the preſent <hi>I</hi> ſhall adviſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, you are where providence hath diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you, and 'twill be beſt for you to follow the tract of God in your own Spirit, and ſtay here till an act of confidence and aſſurance ſhall releaſe you; <hi>for if you ſtruggle or make haſt, you intend your bondage:</hi> be you aſſured that the ſubſtance of what <hi>I</hi> ſaid to you, will bear down heaven and earth before it, and truly till then this old adminiſtration which God hath worn ſo long, he is now uncloathing himſelf of, be removed the preſence of Saints, and that glorious manifeſtation of the Sons of God, which hath entertained the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the creature ſo long, cannot bee as wee have plainly in <hi>Eſay 13. 12. 13. I will
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:44694:67"/>
make a man more precious then fine gold yea, a man then the golden wedge of Ophir; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will ſhake the heavens and the earth, &amp;c.</hi> And in the 14. <hi>It ſhall be as a chaſed Roe, and as a Sheep, that no man takes up, &amp;c.</hi> one thing <hi>I</hi> will add more, becauſe <hi>I</hi> ſee your tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation grows with ſome confidence upon yon, ſince you ſeem to have extinguiſhed <hi>the ſmoaking flax by powering water upon it, and repenting of what you have done;</hi> let me thus farre adviſe, <hi>poure on more water, doe it the ſecond time, doe it the third time; and obſerve if the ſmoaking flax prevaile not upon it; and that ſpark lick it up; and the God that anſwereth by fire, let him bee God. I</hi> could attempt ſuch ſatisfaction in a carnall way; but truth is a more immediate and naked thing, and works beſt without the activity and contribution of the creature; neither will <hi>I</hi> humble God ſo far, as to proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute truths of that nature; its the patience of God they may yet be propoſed to the world: <hi>I</hi> doubt there will a quick providence paſſe upon it, and the word is like to be; <hi>He that hath ears to hear, let him hear; and he that is unjuſt let him be unjuſt ſtill; and he that, &amp;c. Revel. 22. 11, 12. For behold, I come quickly, and my reward is with me to give, &amp;c.</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:44694:67"/>
mans work ſhall be manifeſted by fire, for the day ſhall declare it, becauſe it ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed by fire, and as <hi>Paul</hi> hath it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. in a ſettled expectation, of which <hi>I</hi> poſſeſſe my own Spirit, and your preſent temptation in a great deale of patience and reſt,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="letter">
               <head>Letter 22.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y good friend, I wiſh my oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions had been ſuch, as would have given me leave to have ſeen you ſuddenly, and to have come over as I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed. I deſire you would diſpence with me till <hi>Michaelmaſs,</hi> and then I hope to have a proſperous journey by the will of God to come to you, <hi>both to refreſh and be refreſhed by you; I hope the Lord is a working that in</hi> England <hi>which will e're long give his people ſolid cauſe of refreſhment:</hi> we have already the experience of that which
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:44694:68"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:44694:68"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:44694:69"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:44694:69"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:44694:70"/>
a few dayes ago we did but expect, and ſcarce expected. <hi>I hope, as the Lord removes impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments from without, and paves the way of out peace with the pride and projects of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; ſo he will take away all impediments within: our enemies being not onely thoſe of our own kingdome, but of our own hearts, there being the ſame principles of fleſhly wiſdome and carnall reaſoning againſt the kingdome of Chriſt within us, as there is in the world without us. Doubtleſſe the day of the Lord will be upon every thing that exalts it ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the government of Jeſus Chriſt in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> ſhaddows of all ſorts, begin to flye, and day already diſcloſes, and the openings of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon the Soule are very glorious; and that ſpirituall prediction of the Prophet begins to receive its accompliſhment. Eſa. 25. 7. <hi>The Lord will deſtroy in this mountain the face of the covering caſt over al people.</hi> It concerns us quietly to expect the out-goings of the Spirit in us, and the leadings forth from faith to faith, from glory to glory, from fleſh and form, and letter, to ſpirit, and ſo to more ſpirit, at laſt into all ſpirit, till we have our ſelves in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and our God be all in all. I am ſorry, Sir, I am caſt into ſuch a ſtrieght of time, as I muſt neceſſarily break off; otherwiſe I could
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:44694:70"/>
with ſome delight have entertained my ſelfe with this argument: I mean Gods admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring of us immediately in himſelf; but of this more when I ſee you,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours in the Lord Jeſus.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="letter">
               <head>Letter 23.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Fathers love hath of late been much manifeſted toward me, exceeding hath that glory been in which I have dwelt ſince laſt I ſaw you; my joy unſpeakable, my reſt unutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, my peace unconceiveable:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having therefore received ſuch large and plenteous fillings flowing from the heart of the moſt High; I can do no leſſe than acquaint you with ſome few taſtes and reliſhes of my late enjoyments, as in manner followeth:</p>
               <p>On Munday the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of this inſtant; I was in the Evening at a friends houſe in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge-ſhire,</hi> where, (being in a familiar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:44694:71"/>
with ſome of my acquaintance) it pleaſed the Father ſo freely to unboſome him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in me by ſuch clear demonſtrations of his preſence as I never before beheld; inſomuch that I appeared to my ſelfe as one out of my ſelfe tranſlated into the ſubſtantiall and pure enjoyment of that love and peace which <hi>I</hi> have uſually before, either but onely heard, or at leaſt darkly ſeen and beheld through the vails of outward adminiſtrations.</p>
               <p>That which was ſpoken by me under theſe workings, was faced with ſuch an eivdent appearance of ſpirit and power, as that it ſtruck aſtoniſhment in the hearts of thoſe preſent; ſome thereat guſhing out into teares, others poſſeſſed with ſhaking and trembling; and one there was, who was ſo filled with joy, as that he could not refrain ſinging and leaping; my heart was ſo overcharged with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the moſt High, that <hi>I</hi> deſired a more retyred being; and to that end, withdrew to my Bed, where I thought, I might in my more ſingular addreſſes expend my deſires up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my received glory: I lay down in my Bed with unexpreſſible comfort, being overcome with the beauty of holy delights; <hi>I</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to cover this fire with ſilence; but it grew ſo hot within me, that no longer <hi>I</hi> could
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:44694:71"/>
retain it; but was forced to declare to my Bed-fellow (a friend of mine) how it was with me; <hi>I</hi> told him, <hi>I</hi> was over-come with love; <hi>I</hi> was ſo repleniſhed with divine reſt and conſolation, that <hi>I</hi> could not contain my ſelf: <hi>I began to ſing and rejoyce, being every minute apt to be carried out of my Bed to daunce and leap about the room;</hi> but this noiſe ſoonvaniſhed away by the power of that voice which commanded ſilence; ſaying, <hi>Reſt and be ſtill in thine own Love:</hi> Hereat a deep ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence poſſeſſed me, yet not a jot of my glory diminiſhed, but onely brought under the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of a heavenly ſilence; yea, there was ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in heaven.</p>
               <p>My friend lying by me, was ſuddenly ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized with a miraculous power from above, his body did ſhake and tremble in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as I never ſaw; who declared the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the day of God in a language divine and powerfull, ſometimes ſinging and rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, in ſo much, that the people of the houſe being thereat awakened, wondred what the matter ſhould be.</p>
               <p>All this while, my lovely ſilence conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, yet under unſpeakable enjoyments; my breath was by fits taken from me, and the divine life did ſo overpower the naturall, as
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:44694:72"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:44694:72"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:44694:73"/>
that I expected a daily motion out of this form or body: nay how willing was I to commit my body to the power of an eternall ſleepe, and to enter into that immenſity which was able to comprehend me?</p>
               <p>We ſpent almoſt the whole night, under the power of theſe raptures, while at laſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards morning I felt a timely withdrawing of the rigour and vehemency of this power, which I was made freely willing to part with at the Fathers pleaſure; for I have learned both how to want, and how to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound.</p>
               <p>Yet notwithſtanding to this day there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines a virulent and powerfull impreſſion of the ſame upon my heart, which I hope ſhall never be raced out: I then ſaw, and doe ſtill behold a perfect reconciliation brought forth in me, to all that heretofore I have beene at enmity with; <hi>Hell, Sinne, Death, Divell,</hi> are all in a league with mee; I have fellowſhip with God in all theſe, I care not who knowes it: <hi>Sinne</hi> hath loſt its ſtrength, <hi>Hell</hi> its tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Death</hi> its victory, the <hi>Divell</hi> his enmity, we are all friends, <hi>Hallelujah, God omnipotent reignes in all theſe. Good Lord!</hi> What a poor, low life is that which ſubſiſts onely in thoſe things, that bring forth our advantage? I have
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:44694:73"/>
now learned to live upon the higheſt diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages that may be; <hi>I can fetch life out of death, good out of evill, yea, enjoy light in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, peace in torment, Heaven in Hell;</hi> I know nothing can hurt, nothing can deſtroy in this Mountain where I live; Shall <hi>Sinne?</hi> alas that's to weake, the <hi>Law</hi> which was its ſtrength is departed: it ſhall no more have dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me, for I am not under the <hi>Law,</hi> I can paſſe through all imaginable evill in the light of divine righteouſneſſe, and receive not the leaſt dammage; Shall <hi>Hell?</hi> O its a lake of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable torment, I live in it joyfully, I love it dearly. I know the breath of God as rivers of brimſtone kindles <hi>hell</hi> in me, it burnes, it ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and ſo let it till the will of God be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; I can paſſe through theſe flames, yea lye down amongſt them, and not one haire of my head ſhall periſh by them; I glorifie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the very fires.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> ſhall now deſire you to acquaint my Fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nds with theſe dealings of God towards me, if happily any thing may be given in upon their ſpirits about it. All that <hi>I</hi> have (at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) is this: <hi>I</hi> looke upon it as an evident ſigne of ſome dreadfull appearance of the <hi>Sonne of man;</hi> for theſe two things were given in with much power upon my heart.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:44694:74"/>Firſt, <hi>That the God of peace ſhall tread Satan under feet ſhortly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Lift up your head, your redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption drawes nigh.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Read, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand, Rejoyce.</closer>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="letter">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:44694:74"/>
               <head>24. Letter.</head>
               <head type="sub">A Letter written by a young man about 19. yeares of age, the Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning before he dyed, being <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day-night;</hi> hee was well as was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed about 11. of the clock, and about 2. the next morning dyed, and left a Letter, of which this is a Coppy, with this Superſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>To his dear Siſters, Mrs.</hi> Heſter Langham <hi>Mrs.</hi> Sarah Brewer, <hi>Mrs.</hi> Thomaſon, Fiſon, <hi>and others, the Saints of God, when deceaſed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>EE <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Spouſe</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>loves,</hi> the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> the delight of delights himſelfe, the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> from everlaſting with the Sonnes of men, <hi>Love,</hi> our fountaine with thoſe lovely ſtreames of divine and ſuperna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urall glory,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:44694:75"/>
who now dwels in us and we in him. Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Yet a little, and the world ſeeth me no more, but ye ſee me</hi> (pretious) <hi>for a ſmall ſeaſon, a little while hath this world ſeene mee, but low they ſee me no more, but ye ſhall ſee me, for I am gone to our fathers houſe, to lye in the everlaſting armos of eternall love, in the infinite embraces of eternall ſweetneſſe, to bee there where yee ſhall bee all together with mee, and all Saints to all eternity.</hi> Rejoyce now together for me, <hi>and if you love mee you will rejoyce, becauſe I goe to the Father;</hi> for me indeed to live is Chriſt, but to dye is gaine. And ſure <hi>I</hi> am, that Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> deſire for a long time by a flame of love, hath beene kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled in my ſoule, <hi>even to be diſſolved and to be with Chriſt, which is beſt of all: I now live, yet not I, but Chriſt lives in me;</hi> Loe the the time comes <hi>when I dye, yet not I, but this old man which I carry about with me:</hi> Oh pretious Saints! How ſweet? how pleaſant are the thoughts of death to mee? <hi>Surely ſorrow may be for a night, but joy comes in the morning:</hi> Love is that bond of union, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene mee and my beloved, union is that perfection of love, love throughly deſir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect communion: What now hinders this but death? ſurely this muſt needs be pleaſing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:44694:75"/>
me, being the meanes to ſo lovely an end; <hi>I am here but as a wayfaring man which tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries but for a night;</hi> and ſurely what are the pleaſures of this night at the beſt? They are but darkneſſe in themſelves, and in their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt light but reſemblances of another which is farre greater; <hi>But behold the night is paſt, the day appeares, and I am gone to my beloved, he that ſhould come, is come, and hath not tarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and oh bleſſed, yea thrice bleſſed is his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to me, where I can ſee him face to face, whom my ſoule ſo much longed for:</hi> The vaile is rent, and <hi>I</hi> now no longer ſee him, as in a glaſſe, but in his owne native beauty, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall glory: Bleſſed Saints, <hi>I leave you and goe to my Father, ſurely whether I goe you know, and the way you know;</hi> think it not ſtrange cone rning this my fiery tryall, by death and ſep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ation from you, for <hi>loe the time commeth, in which we ſhall be no more ſeperated, but as we are one, ſo ſhall we ever be, inſeperable from our own beloved. Holy, holy, holy, is the Lord God of Sabbath,</hi> a holy reſt, a Sabbath of eternall reſt, am <hi>I</hi> gone to celebrate; Oh yee holy Saints, the voyce of my Beloved, <hi>behold he comes leaping upon the Hils, and skipping upon the Mountaines, Loe he comes and that quickly, he comes, and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:44694:76"/>
now quickly am I gone,</hi> of all Beloveds, none is like to mine, the melodious voyce ſings ſweetly in mine eare, even of Angels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but that new Song of love, the ſweet lovely Song of Saints, gloriouſly glorified with their Beloved, is harmonious indeed: What ſhall <hi>I</hi> now ſay of theſe things, <hi>I</hi> cannot now fully apprehend them as it is, but am now comprehended of them, therefore lye <hi>I</hi> downe and reſt with this perſwaſion and full conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſealed by the witneſſe of the Spirit unto my Soule, <hi>that what my Beloved is, ſo ſhall I be, and where bee is, thither am I gone:</hi> Then deare Siſters and precious Saints, make haſte and tarry not, that are here on earth in imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, ſo that now in heaven in perfection we may live and for ever enjoy <hi>Joyes unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and full of glory.</hi> Farewell deare <hi>Saints,</hi> farewell, farewell, though I now leave you and goe away from you, yet I ſhall ſee you againe, and when I ſee you, ſo I rejoyce eternally to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with you; in this life I have beene yours, and here together with you; and ſurely death disjoynts not our Spirits, though our Bodies; therefore in another life ſhall we be as members, ſo <hi>Saints</hi> glorified in our glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and with him who is our delight, in whom you are, to whom you are, to whom
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:44694:76"/>
I goe, and with whom wee ſhall remaine, <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> to our <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Deare <hi>Saints</hi> I reſt, and the God of reſt be with your <hi>ſpirits</hi> for ever, and when you ſee this, think on him, who was here your fellow <hi>Diſciple,</hi> but now,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your glorified Brother, WILLIAM LANGHAM.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="letter">
               <head>25. Letter.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Coppy of a Letter, as it was ſent from Mrs. <hi>T. P.</hi> in behalfe of Mrs. <hi>E. P.</hi> To a Congregation of Saints in <hi>London,</hi> under the forme of Baptiſme.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>EAR brethren in the bowels of love and meekneſſe, I kindly ſalute you, wiſhing you an encreaſe of all faithfulneſſe and true knowledge in the myſtery of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> The cauſe of my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent writing is to acquaint you, that provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:44694:77"/>
hath lately brought a letter to my hand, directed to my husband, concerning one Mrs. <hi>P.</hi> once a member with you; which wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſay you, for ſcandalous evils, was caſt out: Now it being ſome yeares ſince it was done, I humbly deſire a little to reaſon with you about the grounds, why this ſtill remains up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſpirits, ſeeing Chriſt ſaith, <hi>forgive yee one another, as I forgive you;</hi> and God is ſaid to remember our ſinnes no more; this therefore is a note of forgiveneſſe, not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member; and ſure we ſhould ſhew our ſelves children of our heavenly father; But further I deſire before the Lord, that you examine your owne hearts in this thing, what your end is in it; if it be that you thinke, ſhe is not worthy to have a livelihood amongſt men; then why doe you not either by the Civill Law (if that will take hold of the offence) or by ſome other way (if nothing will ſatisfie you but her blood) take ſome preſent courſe that may put an end to this great difference? but if you thinke this bee too groſſe, or more then the offence requires; then I beſeech you, for the Lords ſake, to conſider your owne actings in this thing, whether you doe not as much as in you lies, carry on the ſame deſigne (though more cloſly from the eyes of the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:44694:77"/>
world) which ſure before the Lord, can appear no other, but the hunting after her life; nay, is it not more, then to take off one ſingle life at once? for which is greater cruelty, for a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to take a mans life at once? or by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees? and then your ſelves be judges, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your proceedings towards her be not a killing all the day long: for you cannot bee ignorant that ſhe hath no livelihood amongſt men, but what ſhe earnes by her hands: and your defaming her in this manner cannot, in an ordinary way, but deprive her of that, and ſo at laſt bring her blood upon you: If you ſay, you acquaint none but the <hi>Saints</hi> with it, it is evident to the contrary; for your open publiſhing it in the <hi>Counſell of Warre,</hi> cauſed the world to take notice of it, and yet your ſpirits reſt not here; truly deare friends, as the evill ſpirit wrought in her one way, when ſhe was with you; ſo conſider whether the fame ſpirit, doe not highly worke in you at this time another way; the Lord give you underſtanding in all things: But if her life be not that which you aim at, then is it thoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine diſcoveries of life and light, which God makes out to the world by her? if it be ſo, then you are to know, that hee is too ſtrong you ſtrive withall; but about this I would a
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:44694:78"/>
little quere: firſt, whether doe you think, that becauſe ſuch evils were manifeſt in her, when with you; therefore it is impoſſible now that any good ſhould bee brought forth by her? doe you not hope to grow better and better? But ſecondly, is it not Gods u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall way to manifeſt himſelfe there higheſt, where in time paſt he was by the evill ſpirit kept loweſt? yea, doth hee not ſuffer himſelfe for this very end many times, thus to die in appearance, and to leave a ſoule to it ſelfe, that it may ſee what it is in it ſelfe, and learne to die to it ſelfe, that ſo hee may have the more glorious reſurrection in that ſoule? I beſeech you for the Lords ſake to conſider theſe things: As for her outward perſon, I conceive ſhe cares as little for it as you can; therefore you may take your fill of trampling on it; but I beſeech you bee carefull how you medle with the ſpirit that breaths in her; for ſurely bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, I know not what ſpirit manifeſted it ſelfe in her while with you; I am ſure (and I ſpeake nothing but the truth) that I have found a moſt divine ſpirit in her, as farre as <hi>I</hi> could diſcerne, and that which comes to the ſpirit and life of things; and in this me thinks you ſhould rejoyce, for truly, <hi>I</hi> have heard many profeſſors, and ſeene many profeſſions,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:44694:78"/>
but to my knowledge, <hi>I</hi> never heard one come ſo neare the power as ſhee does: <hi>I</hi> doe not ſpeake this as being affected with any perſon, party, or opinion; <hi>I</hi> bleſſe my God <hi>I</hi> am now (in his ſtrength) delivered from that, though ſome have falſly affirmed my being deluded by her; but <hi>I</hi> am confident <hi>I</hi> can ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi> and that not onely repeating the letter, but in truth; <hi>that thoſe things which I have received, have not beene from man, nor woman, nor any other thing, but by the meere revelation of Jeſus Chriſt in mee, God mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting himſelfe in my owne fleſh:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they much wrong both her, and me, that affirme it; but eſpecially they wrong or ſpeake a lye of that God that did it for me: and becauſe I heare it ſo reported amongſt you, I thought good to write one word to cleare it, that ſo whether you will heare, or whether you will forbeare, the word of truth might judge you; give not eare therefore to all you heare, though from brethren, leaſt you be brought into a ſnare; for ſince the defection of the Churches, men, yea good men, have been ſuch lovers of themſelves and their own opinions, that they will ſpeake largely, upon little ground, to keepe up their owne glory, God having not yet undone them; for were
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:44694:79"/>
they once undone men, they would willingly be what God would have them, however the world accounts of them.</p>
               <p>There is another thing which came to my care, that it ſhould be given into the Counſell by your two witneſſes, that the ſaid Mrs <hi>P.</hi> ſhould ſay, that you caſt her out for difference in judgement; and when Collonell <hi>Rich</hi> and Collonell <hi>Hariſon</hi> asked to whom ſhee ſpake it, they ſaid to ſome of <hi>Abington:</hi> Now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed my husband ſaid to you, that he thought ſuch a thing; but when hee came home and ſaw ſo little ground for his thoughts, <hi>I</hi> thinke he had but little comfort in telling you ſo; and then, brethren, if you upon ſuch ſlender grounds ſhould act in this ſtrange manner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her, affirming this thing ſo publikely, <hi>I</hi> thinke you have cauſe to bee humbled for it, and juſtly to repent of your evill; <hi>I</hi> deſire you to beare a little with mee, for truly it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares to mee, rather to bee your rage of ſpirit, then your true love, either to her, or truth; for mee thinkes it would ſavour more of a true Chriſtian ſpirit, if you had firſt ſpoken with her, and have ſeene what change the Lord hath wrought in her, as knowing that <hi>Mary</hi> out of whom ſeuen Divels had beene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly caſt, <hi>was made the firſt meſſenger of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:44694:79"/>
Chriſts Reſurrection;</hi> yea, and ſhe muſt bring it to the Apoſtles, and not the Apoſtles to her: You ſay, in your letter, <hi>that you left her to the judgement of the great day;</hi> and <hi>I</hi> beſeech you, brethren, doe you not, againe take her into your owne daie? for truly <hi>I</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that daie in a meaſure hath come upon her, and the Lord himſelfe is at worke with her; therefore doe not feare but the worke will be well done; onely we, as well as ſhee, muſt have patience in it, and ſurely this is the confidence that <hi>I</hi> have concerning her, that ſhe hath ſeen evill in that eſtate ſhe walked in with you; and certainly, God is good to her in this, ſhewing her what an abominable ſpirit of wickedneſſe may bee hid under the greateſt practiſes and profeſſions of externals; not that theſe are the cauſe of it; no, <hi>the gold and the ſilver is mine,</hi> ſaith the Lord; but wee beſtowing it upon our lovers, and making our ſelves great with his ornaments, he is fain, in love to us, to take us from them, or they from us, and ſo finde out a more ſprirituall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration to perfect us in: Oh the infinite riches of our God! where doth his bounty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd? ſure his waies of love are unſearchable, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d his paths of mercy, in which he followes anore fallen man: and poor backſliding ſoules,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:44694:80"/>
are paſt finding out; how narrow are our ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities? we judge as men; We may think as ſome did of <hi>David,</hi> that there is no help for ſuch things in God; but all things in truth will be found poſſible with him, even where they are altogether paſt our thoughts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, and become to us impoſſible; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you therefore be perſwaded to bow down to him; I know you are conſcious, that all judgement is not committed unto you, and therefore it is poſſible you may not judge right in this thing; for truly, brethren, we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive many things even by the letter it ſelf, &amp; yet not living in that ſpirit that writ the letter, we may erre; I pray do not miſtake me, as if I would any way ſpeak ſlightly of the letter, farther than it ſpeaks of it ſelf; no, I bleſſe the Father for it, and by ſweet experience can ſay, that <hi>I</hi> was never ſo confirmed in it, now the Lord hath drawn me to him out of it, even in that ſpirit that wrote it; I am for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable uſe of it, but I would not abuſe it; I am ſure, thoſe men that would ſet it above the ſpirit, can hardly free themſelves from that thing; I hope, therefore you will not count it your excellency to walk in the letter, but rather deſire the Lord to perfect you in that ſpirit that writes the letter, for then and never
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:44694:80"/>
till then, ſhall we be able to walk by it aright, and ſpeak of the letter truly.</p>
               <p>I have not yet acquainted my husband with your letter, I ſhall wait upon God what an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to receive from you: for truly, dear bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, upon ſerious deliberation, I know not how to approve my ſelf faithfull in the eyes of God, to my brethren here, if I ſhould deliver it; for God having put it into my hand, I muſt alſo ſee clearnes from him before I part with it: for though, bleſſed be the father, we have a ſweet hopefull people amongſt us that wait upon God, and have fellowſhip one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; yet whether they may digeſt ſuch things as you write of, I really queſtion; therefore it would be unfaithfulnes in me, if I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending an evill to them, or any other, ſhould not as much as in me lies, prevent it; and this I ſhall doe, by detaining the Letter, till fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manifeſtation from God what to do with it; Doe not judge me in this thing, I beſeech you; I have one Judge, even the Lord, and he that put it into my hand, will a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> length clear my integrity in it; I have nothing to doe for my ſelf in it, the Lord knows, only to find out (if it may be) how I may approve my ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aithfull to men in the Lord and for the Lords <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:44694:81"/>Your deſire I exceedingly like, that we may be kept from errours, and the Lord keep us all from errours, but who muſt ſhew us what errour is, but the God of truth himſelf? we have lived in errour, and have ſuckt them in from our cradles; and yet who will ſpeak ſo much againſt error as we, ſtating our ſelves ſtill in the truth: My ſweet friends, the day of truth is but now dawning upon us, and how is it oppoſed, even by thoſe that are children of truth, in their meaſure? yet wee have all looked for it, and prayed together for it a long time; but truly now, we will not own our prayers, but turn away our face from our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, becauſe he comes not in ſuch a garb as we imagined he would, when we know its his prerogative to cloath himſelf with what fleſh or garment he pleaſes: brethren, what would you have? doe you not know that a glorious day hath been ſpoken of ever ſince the Prophets, and the Apoſtles? Though the day was dawned upon them, yet they bid their hearers not to be terrified, as if that day were near; for ſaith he, there muſt be a falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way firſt; and that wicked one be revealed; notwithſtanding <hi>Peter</hi> could them that he was a partaker or that glory, that ſhould be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards revealed; However (ſaith he, you
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:44694:81"/>
have a more ſure word of Propheſie, to which yee doe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll to take heed; as if he had ſaid: <hi>Brethren, we have been with the Lord in the mount, and have beheld that excellent glory, but yet to you that have not ſo ſeen Chriſt, there is a more ſure word of Propheſie; for viſions and revelations doe moſt eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme and ſtrengthen thoſe that have them; but here is a word that is ſpoken to all, and is as a light ſhining in a dark place, therefore you do well to take heed to it till the day dawn, and the day ſtar ariſe in you own hearts, and you be ſwallowed up with that glory, that now you expect and wait for; onely know this, that no private ſpirit can underſtand theſe Scriptures that ſpeak of that day, it muſt be the ſpirit of God alone; let us ceaſe from our own ſpirits therefore, for they are ſelfiſh and private, bound up to this and that, and ſo would confine God alſo; but his Spirit is as large as himſelf; its without bounds; its neither here nor there diſtinct, but it is individually every where.</hi> But that which I deſire you to conſider from theſe Scriptures is, that this day of falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way hath been; and all the world hath won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred after the beaſt, ſince the Apoſtles time; therefore how near may we expect our glory; we ſhould not be troubling our ſelves there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:44694:82"/>
ſtill with falling away, but now look for a riſing, for ſure man hath had his day, and now the Lord will have his day: now ſeeing this day of the Lord muſt have a dawning, and ſome Diſciples may be taken up into the Mount, before other ſome; it ſhould teach us not to judge our brethren, that ſpcak of higher injoyments then we have, for we being behinde ſhould rather judge our ſelves, ſeeing we are more in the day of man, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our ſelves ſo to be, ſtill looking for, and haſtening to the day of God, in which we may act ſelf, or ſelfiſhly, no longer, but our God may bring forth his own righteouſneſſe in us: and truly, brethren, you may be ſatisfied in this, that we are very induſtrious to keep our ſelves from errour, but we know that in his ſtrength we ſhall be perfected, and when him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf comes and ſpeaks, then ſhall we know that it is he; and truly brethren, I would not have you infidels but believing; this day hath taken ſome unawares, and though many may have it in notion, yet I am ſure, that ſome have it in power.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> have one thing more to you concerning your letter, and truly <hi>I</hi> cannot but wonder at it, that is, how you durſt ſo peremptorily to judge the woman that ſhe brought a deluſion
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:44694:82"/>
for a viſion of God, I beſeech you conſid er ſeriouſly before the Lord, whether it was ſo or no, before you make it ſo publike, and ſend it forth with the authority of a Church: ſurely friends, you will much abuſe the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of your Church, in affirming meer ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition for truth; the Lord be pleaſed to open your eyes in this thing; it may be your father in mercy deſires, a little to plead with you by a weak inſtrument, and therefore put the letter into my hand, that ſo he might put ſome ſtop to your furious driving; and truly I can look upon it no other wayes; therefore willingly meet your God in this mercifull act towards you; for if you doe not, the dumb Aſſe next time may reprove you; I confeſſe, ſoules, <hi>I</hi> am the weakeſt of all, a poore undone ſoule in my ſelf; the Lord alone take all the glory, yet if I may be uſefull, as being one of the body, in keeping you from doing greater evils, I ſhall be willing and rejoyce, though <hi>I</hi> go under ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great an odium my ſelf; for ſure friends, account of me how you will, I am one of you &amp; tenderly affect you, and in this thing would have God truly exalted: For this grace is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me to love truth under any appearance, though indeed, that may ſometimes appear to men to be truth which I cannot cloſe with;
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:44694:83"/>
but I mean any appearance that my God comes in, and I hope ſhall be more and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in it; and indeed it is ſweet to me that he hath given me, through mercy, to know his voyce from a ſtranger; It may be the world may judge me for it, becauſe it comes not in their form, but I ſhall reſt in the Lord: well brethren, if you ſee mercy to you in that which the Lord hath ſpoken by me, receive it and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in him; it may be, I may prove to you as <hi>Abigail</hi> did to <hi>David,</hi> keep you from ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding blood, and from avenging your ſelves with your own hand, the Lord ſhew us therefore what that ſcripture meaneth, <hi>I will have mercy and not ſacrifice:</hi> there be many things in the letter of the ſcripture, which we through weaknes may think to be ſacrifice as the Phariſees did, when God abhors it, and will have none of it, in ſuch a time as he cals for mercy; therefore he bids us learn what that meaneth: we may have it, &amp; read it &amp; ſpeak it, but to learn the inſide of it, learn what it mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, will be our comfort, and our Crown; and truly my dear friends, <hi>I</hi> am perſwaded, that this is a time, in which, mercy is required of us towards our Siſter, and not ſuch ſacrifice: If you pleaſe to ſend me a word of anſwer, leave it with Mr. <hi>C.</hi> I doe not think it fit as
<pb n="371" facs="tcp:44694:83"/>
yet, that you acquaint my husband with it, not for unlawfulneſſe ſake, but inconveniency; for ſurely brethren, I am not willingly carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to give you or him, or any one offence; onely as the Lord manifeſts it to be his will, and then I muſt leave Father, and mother, and all, and cleave to him. Let me have your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer as ſoon as you can: but I beſeech you, do not anſwer me, but the Lord, and then ſee how you can juſtifie your ſelves; in him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall I wait for it, and dear ſouls, though I am nothing, and can doe nothing in my ſelf; yet I beſeech you doe not reject any word of truth, love and ſincerity that God ſends by my hand. <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>He did not reject the cauſe of his Maid ſervant, when it came before him,</hi> though the word ſaith, <hi>they contended with him:</hi> I can give you more ſatisfaction, if you pleaſe, how I came by the letter; <hi>I</hi> am ſure it was unexpected by me, onely the Lord would have it ſo; and therfore all your care muſt ſerve the Lords deſignes, to bring it to my hand when my husband was not in town: doe not therefore look upon me, but look to the Lord, &amp; uſe me as kindly as <hi>Job</hi> did his ſervant, reject not my cauſe, for ſurely it is not mine: <hi>I</hi> leave
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:44694:84"/>
you to the Lord, whom <hi>I</hi> deſire rightly to guide you in this thing, and am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your ſincere loving Siſter and ſervant, from the greateſt to the meaneſt of you, T. P.</signed>
                  <dateline>Abington, <date>26. March 1649.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="letter">
               <head>26. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Deare Friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ngagements from a true principle are not eaſily diſlolved, and while we hold the head, we cannot let goe the members. <hi>I</hi> have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered you in the union of life and truth; from whence flow my unfeigned reſpects to you, and wherein conſiſts the true enjoyment of your ſelf: Vanity of vanity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſeth between God and us, while we are below, and vexeth our unquiet ſpirits; ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contentment in earthly relations, we wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:44694:84"/>
too and fro, and return empty; but when we cloſe with the divine will, our diſtractions are compoſed, the commotions of our diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pred hearts are all ſweetly ſilenced. Friend, when you have (in the ſpirit) aſcended farre above all heavens, when you are above all, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that God hath made and (for a time) alſo ordained you to uſe, then may you, and then will you be able to deſcend into the loweſt parts of the earth, and from thence again riſe to the higheſt glory; Then will you have a true ſweet and comfortable uſe of the meaneſt condition in the world, out of which you ſhall mount to the cleareſt enjoyment of the greateſt happineſſe, and by a continuall intercourſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween heaven and earth, you will at laſt come to inherit the utmoſt, large and full extent of the Lords dominions. If you were confined to that heaven onely, as it hath been recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the generall notion you would be ſtreightned in your borders, and be deprived of part of your portion and poſſeſſion; for the earth as well as the heaven is filled with the glory of God: from which if you were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, you muſt neceſſarily want that peice of your right, whereof <hi>you were made an heir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe.</hi> When the ladder of our eternall union is ſet between Heaven and Earth, between the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:44694:85"/>
divine and humane nature, then may we both aſcend and deſcend, one as freely as the other: our heavenly ſtate will not diſdain our earthly, nor our earthly hinder our heavenly; <hi>the true Angelicall life hath ſweet communion with God in both.</hi> Trouble, afflictions, and croſses in the world will adminiſter conſolation, and be all your ſervants, helpers of your joy. God will be all, Union unto him cannot be divided; the wings of the morning are not ſwift enough to outflie him; the utmoſt parts of the earth, the fartheſt diſtance of ſenſe, the broad Sea, the greateſt confuſion of minde, the wide wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the moſt ſolitary ſadneſſe of heart can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hide from his preſence; Nay, if you goe downe into the Hell of horrour, your Ioule ſhall not be left there; his right hand of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and ſpirit of holineſſe, will raiſe you up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. I have endeavoured to diſcharge my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects to you, in theſe ſhort and ſudden lines, being now hindred from enlarging by the courteſie and viſites of my friends. My re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of love preſented—</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>I am, Your ſervant in Truth.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>Aug. 20. 1649.</date>
                  </dateline>
Copi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haec mut at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> mutandis typis mandetur.</closer>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="letter">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:44694:85"/>
               <head>27. Letter.</head>
               <head type="sub">To I. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>EARE and loving Friend; whom I deſire to own and to be one with &amp; in the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Son,</hi> in one eternall inviſible and ever-ruling Spirit, in and with which Spirit we are to walk, live &amp; abide in, after we are made one with it, which is and muſt bee an inward, true and inviſible walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and according to an inward, true and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible rule, and not after an outward and worldly manner, as the worldlings doe; <hi>For my Kingdome is not of this world,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt, my Kingdome is not of obſervation, and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rudiments,</hi> for it is within you that conſiſts not in any outward rule or practiſe, all the true rules and directions of the Spirit is within, it is viſible, the truth of all things is within, the outward is not the truth, but an Image of the truth, therefore to walke in outward forms, or ordinances, is but to walke in an Image and
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:44694:86"/>
not in the truth it ſelfe, but to walke in the truth is to walke in the ſpirit, and if in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit then in God, for God is a ſpirit, and hee is the truth of the ſpirit and he that will be one with God muſt bee one with him in the ſpirit and in truth, as it is eſſentiall in God, or elſe there can be no perfection, and then no true walking with God, to be one with God, is to be nothing ones ſelfe, and to walk with God, is to walke out of ones ſelfe: <hi>Enoch</hi> walked with <hi>God</hi> and was not, for <hi>God</hi> tooke him, he was not; that is, hee was not himſelfe: No man can walke with <hi>God</hi> while he is himſelfe, a man as man cannot be ſaid to walke with <hi>God;</hi> he may walke with man, but not with <hi>God,</hi> nothing can be ſaid to walke with <hi>God,</hi> but what is one, in and with God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt bee as <hi>God;</hi> for none can walke with <hi>God,</hi> but <hi>God; No man hath ſeen the Father, but the Sonne;</hi> hee that aſcended is the ſame that deſcended, <hi>no man hath nor never ſhall ſee the Father, but the Sonne:</hi> Then none can be ſaid to walke with <hi>God,</hi> but <hi>Jeſus Chriſt who is God.</hi> And this walking is inviſible, that is, a communion of ſpirit in man; one man may have communion with another as man, but none can have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with <hi>God,</hi> but <hi>God; light cannot have
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:44694:86"/>
communion with darkneſſe, nor darkneſſe with light, but light hath communion with it ſelfe: Therefore that we are in the light, let us walk as Children of the light, and not as the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of darkneſſe.</hi> But you will ſay, <hi>Doe wee not walke with God in Ordinances?</hi> I anſwer, that <hi>ordinances</hi> are not <hi>light, truth</hi> nor <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and therefore wee cannot walke with <hi>God</hi> in them; wee cannot walke with <hi>God</hi> in any thing but in the <hi>light,</hi> in the <hi>truth,</hi> and in the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> nor none can walke with <hi>God</hi> in theſe things, but the <hi>divine ſpirit,</hi> or <hi>inward man,</hi> which is of <hi>God,</hi> and one with <hi>God;</hi> to walke with and in <hi>God,</hi> is to walke in the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>ordinances</hi> you cannot ſay are the <hi>truth,</hi> no more then you can ſay the <hi>ſcripture</hi> is the <hi>truth,</hi> but if you will make it <hi>truth,</hi> you muſt make it <hi>God,</hi> for there is but one <hi>truth,</hi> and that is <hi>God: One God and Father of all, one Lord, one Faith and one Baptiſme, and all but one God and one truth. God</hi> as he is in the <hi>word Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> is the <hi>truth,</hi> and if we have heard of him, and been taught by him as the <hi>truth</hi> is in <hi>Jeſus;</hi> then ſhall wee ſay, that the <hi>ſcripture</hi> is not <hi>truth,</hi> but it tels us what is the <hi>truth;</hi> it ſaith, <hi>It is life eternall to know God, the true God, then to walke in the truth, is to know the truth, and to know the truth is</hi>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:44694:87"/>
                  <hi>know God onely, and having knowne God, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> know how to walke with God, and no man can know God, but God, no man can know the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but the Sonne, and hee to whom the Sonne will reveale him. And the Sonne hath not truly revealed the Father to man, till man through Chriſt is become the Sonne of God, and being the Sonne of God, hee knowes God, and is knowne of God, and ſo is one with God, whereby he hath acceptance to walk with God.</hi> We ſhould take it ill of them that tell us wee know not <hi>God,</hi> but when we come to know him indeed as <hi>God</hi> in his owne eternall and eſſentiall being, wee ſhall then confeſſe that we never knew him before, we have had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thoughts we have known <hi>God,</hi> when alas we have known nothing of him, as he ought to be known; to know God in any forme, or ordinance, nay in any created excellency, even the higheſt manifeſtation that ever wee had of him among the creatures, is but as an imagined or formall knowledge, which can be no perfect knowledge, it is no true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>God,</hi> to know him in any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low himſelfe, below the divine and eſſentiall being of <hi>God;</hi> all things below himſelfe are imperfect and can give no true teſtimony of him, we receive tokens from men, and letters
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:44694:87"/>
from men by which we come to have ſome kind of knowledge of them, but if we never ſee the perſon, wee can have no true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him: the greateſt manifeſtation that ever we have of <hi>God,</hi> or the greateſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge we can have of him, though it boby <hi>Angels</hi> if it be not by himſelfe, it is not a true knowledge, and can produce no true happines, for they are all but as meſſengers ſent from him and is not himſelfe, and till he comes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his owne ſubſtance that wee ſee him as he is in himſelfe, a <hi>God</hi> above and beyond all gifts and graces which but as meſſengers were ſent from him, wee ſee him not and then cannot know him as we ought. <hi>I am not the Chriſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>John, I am but ſent before him, to prepare the way for him, and as be increaſeth, I muſt decreaſe, I muſt be nothing, that he may be all.</hi> Therefore while wee ſee ordinances any thing, gifts, graces, manifeſtations or any thing below <hi>God</hi> himſelfe to be any thing, ſo long we ſee not <hi>God</hi> to be all, and then know him not as <hi>God,</hi> wee may know him in all things after a manner, but it is an outward externall knowledge, and not a ſpirituall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward knowledge, and therefore no true knowledge; yet this is the knowledge wee have of him in ordinances, even an eternall
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:44694:88"/>
litterall knowledge, and according to this ſo we walke, and not according to <hi>truth</hi> and perfection. But you will then ſay, <hi>Is it not the will of God, that we ſhould walke in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</hi> I anſwer that in way of permiſſion, it may be for a time, yet not for ever; but the will of <hi>God</hi> goes further<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>for this is the will of God, even your ſanctification, that all that are his ſhould bee as himſelfe, for bee yee perfect, as he is perfect;</hi> perfection conſiſts not in ordinances, nor in any created excellence, but in <hi>God</hi> onely, which is an uncreated glory; <hi>therefore be ye perfect, as he is perfect, for that is the will of your God,</hi> and ought to be the deſire of all his, <hi>to be perfect, as he is perfect, to walke as he walks, and to know as he knowes,</hi> and in this we ſhall be like unto <hi>God,</hi> that wee may have fellowſhip with him, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſayth, <hi>walke in the light, as he is in the light; and then you ſhall have fellowſhip with us, and truly our fellowſhip is with the Father, and the Sonne,</hi> and this is a fellowſhip above all ordinances, and above all revealed things; a man cannot have fellowſhip with God, and converſe with him as God, till hee is ſeperated from all relation. It is ſaid in <hi>Prov. 18. 1. that through deſire a man hauing ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated himſelfe, ſeeketh and entermidleth with
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:44694:88"/>
all wiſdome.</hi> That is with God, a man cannot ſeek or intermeddle with the Creator till he is ſeperated from the creature. But you will ſay, are we not then to make uſe of the creature, nor any created thing? I anſwer, in a temporall way you may; but all that while, you will have but a temporall union with them, nor in them; there can be no true union with God in the creature, no not in any created glory whatſoever. <hi>For all is as graſſe, and as graſſe it withereth, becauſe the ſpirit of the Lord blows upon it; and all the joy and comforts, that I have thought, I have found in them, is but as a blaſt before the Almighty God,</hi> the creature, nay, the excellencyes of creatures, or creature comforts were made only for the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and not for the ſoule, not as to finde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in them; no, nothing can be food to a ſoule, but the eternall inviſible being of God; for inviſible things muſt be fed from invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible powers; and the ſoule is as inviſible as God; for it is God: it is and muſt be that dependence which we have upon God, and this would fall if not fed by God and from God; therefore it is one with God. The Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and ſtreams, which is one with the Seas, would ſoon faile, if not fed from the Sea. So would the ſoule of man, if it were not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:44694:89"/>
fed from its own natural principle from God, who is the ſea and fountain of Soules; and now an Ordinance or any other thing but God cannot bring comfort to a ſoule: a man may take ſome delight in them, but it is but a fancy or ſome naturall or outward affection that he hath to them, and not for any ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all comfort he findeth in them: he may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps count it ſpirituall, but the ſpirit cannot count ſo of it; the ſpirit cannot delight to be in any thing, but in its own element, which is an element above all created things, fleſh and ſpirit cannot dwel together without interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one of another: therefore to tie the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to have communion with God in an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, is to keep him in bondage: the Church which is below, is in bondage with her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; but the Church which is above in the ſpirit is ſure, which is the mother of us all; therefore to binde the ſpirit, to an Ordinance, or to any thing below it ſelf, which is below God, is to keep him in bondage: Men may walk in Ordinances, or in Forms, or in the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of things. But all this while their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion is but an Image, an outward form or Image to the communion of ſpirits, it is but a naturall communion which typifies a Church in the ſpirit. So that it is not our perfection
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:44694:89"/>
to walk in Ordinances; becauſe by them God is vailed from us, and we ſee him not in his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen manifeſt glory, and ſo are not changed into the likeneſſe of him, but remain ſtill as ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Pilgrims. Therefore let us with the Apoſtle, forget that which is behinde, and preſſe forward to that which is before, which is to ſee God in his open manifeſt glory, and not in the glory of an Ordinance, or any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thing for they are but vailes which doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe and hide the glory of God from us, that we ſee him not as we ought; whereby we might have communion with him: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God doth rend that vaile, and caſt that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way as moth eaten, as vain helpleſſe things; and now he ſhews himſelf with a new gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>with the robes of righteouſneſſe and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, with ſalvation in the middeſt of them; with a full manifeſtation of all his attributes in one eſſentiall, inviſſible and eternall glory for his Saints:</hi> and he that will now ſee God, to have ſweet fellowſhip and communion with him, muſt ſee him in all, in all this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, without the help of any Ordinance or crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thing whatſoever; for that hath been and is ſtill the cauſe of our ignorance of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we never look for him to come in this open glory. But we lye ſtill expecting of
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:44694:90"/>
him to come in old apparell, and not in new; in an ordinance, and not without, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our ſelves. <hi>That when the Bridegroom comes, like fooliſh Virgins are found unprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, with our lamps neither oyled nor lighted, but barren and fruitleſſe;</hi> and ſo are left hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and comfortleſſe: And with this, I ſhall take my leave at this time, and ſhall with all commit you and the reſt of our fellow mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in Chriſt, to the onely fellowſhip of the Father and the Son together in one eternall and inviſible glory, in which fellowſhip I deſire to own you, and to walk with you, and to heare from you, and ſo fare you well.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. C.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="letter">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:44694:90"/>
               <head>28. Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Received yours of an old date; you are conſtant in loving, ſlow in expreſſing and declaring; in which, though yet you are full; I doe own your love in all, both letter and token, and wiſh I had to make you a ſutable return</p>
               <p>Your trouble, is about Ordinances; <hi>You want them, and yet cannot uſe them, you think you want them at leaſt;</hi> but it is the annoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you want, not <hi>John,</hi> much leſſe his water; you have the annointing, and need not that any man teach you, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 21. It abideth in you, it will appear, the box in which it is, will be broken, and perfume the whole honſe: The box is your heart, whileſt you are looking without: In that condition you are, the Poets <hi>Tantalus</hi> is your picture and your motto. The Woolf by the ears, you neither dare hold nor let go; ſtay a while, and your Candle wil be
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:44694:91"/>
lighted; The Lord is your light, the annoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which you have received of him, abideth in you, and the ſame teacheth you all things.</p>
               <p>You ſay, <hi>Why you dare not uſe Ordinances, becauſe you finde them not in their exactnes, according to the Primitive pattern.</hi> Do you think to be perfect in the fleſh? I know you doe not: Why then doe you expect exactnes here? All externall things will be matter of <hi>doubtfull diſputation, 1 Rom.</hi> 14. and we ſhall not come into reſt, and out of diſpute, till we come into the ſpirit, where is both unity and reſt; till circumciſion and uncircumciſion be nothing; and the new creature and faith wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by love, all, we ſhall not be eſtabliſhed: <hi>He that doth it is God, who hath alſo annointed us, and ſealed us, and given the earneſt of the ſpirit in our hearts. 2 Cor.</hi> 1. Till we ſee and acknowledge God not limitted to make out himſelf by ordinance, if not to be gone out of them, as to any manifeſtation of life, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by them, we cannot be at reſt.</p>
               <p>God will take us out of all our childiſh work, before we have made any thing of it; and are theſe better things then rudiments and elements in our childiſh ſtate? a bondage that the father is pleaſed his children (that are heires of all) ſhould be in, till the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:44694:91"/>
by him; whileſt we are Babes, we have no trouble in them, onely about our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe; as we grow up, doubts grow, and trouble and diſputes about them, about their pure inſtitution, and at laſt we come to look into their worth, and ſet the ſigne and the ſpirit diſtinct before us; and ſo come by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to be crucified to them, and they to us; and are ſenſible of a bondage, and are making into the liberty of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>And whereas you mention, <hi>the Primitive pattern, as to theſe ordinances:</hi> There is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a pattern to Babes, or thoſe that have to doe with them; for theſe outward things are the milk, and not the ſtrong meat; and if the Apoſtles and thoſe anointed with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, then, could have ſpoken to their converts, other wiſe then as unto carnall, they would not have ſpoken earthly things; nor dealt with them in thoſe principles, from whence they are calling them, to make forward to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and blame them for their <hi>dullneſſe,</hi> Hebr. 6.</p>
               <p>The old adminiſtration, was weak, weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and tyring, and therefore God went out of it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. &amp; ſo wil he hence, when he hath brought us to ſee the weaknes &amp; feel wearines; he is calling ſuch into the ſpirit, <hi>Come unto</hi> 
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:44694:92"/>
                  <hi>riod to ordinances, goſpell as well as legall.</hi> Hee will <hi>once more ſhake Heaven and Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And is not hee doing that in you? and till that comes <hi>that remaines,</hi> ſurely we are <hi>to worſhip at the doore of the Tabernacle,</hi> and then will his remove appeare plainly; which by want of enjoyment in Ordinances is onely ſuſpected, or conjectured. I conſent unto you fully, <hi>that the want of enjoyments there, are no rule ſafe enough to walke by.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſay, <hi>You have ſound communion with God in Ordinances, and without; The laſt more immediate and the ſweeteſt:</hi> To this God cals you by ſome taſtes, and will ſettle you there in due time, <hi>the time appointed of the Father,</hi> the time of the acknowledgement of the Son of God in you.</p>
               <p>You ſay, <hi>that your thoughts worke about Gods ſilence in Ordinances, as upon this reaſon to humble us, as in the Iſralites hunger,</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to you, and ſo to prepare us for bread from heaven that needs no ſowing, threſhing, winnowing, nor ſhall be gathered by Homer, or meaſure.</p>
               <p>You obſerve <hi>with trouble, the declining of ſome, who leave ordinances, to the deniall of Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:44694:92"/>Wonder not that when God cals ſome to himſelf in a more immediate enjoyment with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ordinances, that the Devill ſhould bee playing his part there, in <hi>Jann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> and <hi>Jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your diſlike of <hi>the common pleading for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,</hi> I wonder not at, becauſe it is done in oppoſition to the ſpirit, which they onely ſerve to, and is the life of them, and that tels me that <hi>that Heaven is foulding up as a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and hee comming forth that changes it not.</p>
               <p>You ſay, <hi>there hath beene a glory in that adminiſtration,</hi> I grant it, and that it yet is to ſome, yea many, and they doe well to waite for glory there where they finde it appearing to them; I call off none fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ordinances, I judge not thoſe that profeſſe themſelves cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led off; I know not where abouts I am, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in <hi>viſion,</hi> but ſometimes I hope in <hi>dreames,</hi> the old mans ſtate, and ſo under the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>The laſt thing you mention, is your ſeruples about <hi>Ordinances,</hi> which are tor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>as an hedge of thornes</hi> ſet by the Lord in your way; to turn you backe again from thoſe things which we have more or leſſe idollized and ſet up in his place.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:44694:93"/>I have performed your deſire, and you may looke upon me as <hi>Lazarus</hi> quickened, but <hi>bound hand and foot with grave cloaths:</hi> what life and liberty I have, it muſt be to ſerve the Saints, and therefore account me ever ready to ſerve you.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>Auguſt 18. 1649.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="letter">
               <head>Letter 29.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear and much eſteemed,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Father hath unboſomed ſuch a glory to me, ſince I ſaw you laſt; that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but admire at it; it was as I was walking alone, the power of my Father was ſeen in an exceeding glory, ſo that I could not tell how to contain it, my veile was too nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to receive it; I have had many diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of glory ſince, and have been in many fires, and burnt very ſweetly, and conſum'd
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:44694:93"/>
very joyfull: I deſire to live as well in Hell as in Heaven; and the greater Hell, the greater Heaven: I rejoyce exceedingly in the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing burnings: one breath of my Father makes both Heaven and Hell; but this is that my Father hath written in my heart, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting deliverance is at hand; but firſt, the Lord will cover the Earth with darkneſſe, and with groſſe darkneſſe the people, and ſuch black clouds of darknes will our Father cloath him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with: that none but thoſe that ſee with the eye of the Lord, ſhall be able to ſee him in the thick darknes: <hi>The ſmoak of the Beaſt aſcends out of the bottomleſſe pit, and wrath from the Almighty is upon her; and I cannot but rejoyce and ſing Hallelujah, Hallelujah, all praiſe be given to him that ſits on the thron for ever; and when you ſee theſe things done, then lift up your heads, the day of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption is at hand;</hi> I ſee them performed, I ſee them finiſhed and brought forth into power, and I rejoyce in the work of the Lord. I ſee the reſtored eſtate of our bringing forth with mighty power; that wee ſhall ſee all things good, that the Saints ſhall know no evill; for my part I know no evill, I ſee all things good; I know nothing but good in all the world; the Lord doth all things well,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:44694:94"/>
whether in Earth or in Heaven, and that that hath ſwallowed us up, we are now ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it up; I am ſwallowing Death, Hell, and the Grave up; that now I am able to play with Satan; He is but a Reed in my hands. I have been really cloathed upon, and morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity ſwallowed up into life; and when this glory comes forth, it will judge the world, and ſilence them; our glory is their torment, and our Heaven is their Hell: Thus I have given you an account of the preſent diſcoveries of my Father, and reſt in your heart,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Clem.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="song">
            <pb facs="tcp:44694:94"/>
            <head>A New Song.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Am that I am,</l>
               <l>All that you heare and ſee;</l>
               <l>I was, now is, and ſo ſhall bee</l>
               <l>All to Eternitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>2. Good is the Word, the Word is Good,</l>
               <l>God and the Word are one;</l>
               <l>The rule is true and even ſo</l>
               <l>All that you look upon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>3. This Word is Good, this Good is God,</l>
               <l>This Good is all you ſee;</l>
               <l>If otherwiſe I ſhould it owne,</l>
               <l>Where would the freedome be?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>4. Now herein is the freedome juſt,</l>
               <l>Thus knowing light to ſee,</l>
               <l>That all is Good, this all is God,</l>
               <l>This Good hath made us free.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>5. Then entertein this freedome juſt,</l>
               <l>In pure love for to bee;</l>
               <l>Which pure love is the perfect Good</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto Eternitie.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
